<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-10-13T03:49:48+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Pranay Gundam</title><entry><title type="html">bypassing bot detection through mouse movements</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/bypassing-bot-mouse-detection/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="bypassing bot detection through mouse movements"/><published>2024-10-12T23:47:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-12T23:47:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/bypassing-bot-mouse-detection</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/bypassing-bot-mouse-detection/"><![CDATA[<p>I’m currently on a bus to DC for the weekend and have gotten tired on working on econ things for now so here I am talking about this. I had a conversation with work friend last week about CAPTCHA and RECAPTCHA, you know I had to pull the CMU flex and talk about how the guy who made that was a CMU professor and how they managed to make hella money off of it from the New York Times, and the conversation strayed into the general realm of bot detection. He was telling me how for some of the new Google bot detection stuff they track the movement of your cursor when you go to interact with whatever puzzle they give you. The very basic main idea is that humans don’t move in perfect straight lines and “botters” (if that is indeed the adjective to describe them, maybe botists or botmens/botwomans/botpeople) are sometimes too lazy to bother making the cursor move in some more nuanced way. At a higher level even if the botter were to make the cursor move in curves there is still a mathematical difference between a perfect curve and imperfect ones.</p> <p>This got me thinking about strategies to make the cursor move in a nonbotlike manner. After doing more research later, I also found out that the speed of one’s cursor at different parts of the path is also a big tell in differentiating between a persion and a bot. Specifically a human tends to move the cursor faster the further they are from the target and then make smaller slower micro adjustments the closer they get. I tried paying attention to my mouse movements for a bit and saw that the “strategy” I used was also dependent on the size and position of the target. Meaning my approach curve and speed was not independent of the position and also very dependent on the size. For example, when I want to manually click on a tab to switch to on chrome, I tend to move the cursor very fast with disregard for vertical precision because there’s no such thing as vertically overshooting a target that is already at border of the screen. In another case, when I’m not conscioulsy aware of where my cursor is positioned initially, I will move the cursor directly horizontal or directly vertical until I visually see where it is and then error correct respectively. At it’s core, I feel like human behavior is all about iterative error correction which reminds me a lot of stochastic gradient descent.</p> <p>I’ll talk about a few methods that came to mind in order of simple to most complicated but ultimately from my qualitative view of how I personally move the cursor, I think the key to acting like a human is to act “stochastically predictable”.</p> <p><strong>1. Straight line movement</strong> This is pretty simple to understand, there is a target pixel at coordinates \((x_T,y_T)\) and the cursor starts at coordinates \((x_0, y_0)\). We then draw a simple line between the two points and move the cursor at some speed (or variable speed). Specifically, we choose some time unit \(t'\) we want the total travel time of the cursor to be and some update frequency \(s'\) (meaning every \(s'\) milliseconds we update the position of the cursor). This means that at the i-th update of the cursor, it is at the coordinates \(\left(i\cdot\frac{s'(x_T - x_0)}{t'}, i\cdot\frac{s'(y_T - y_0)}{t'}\right)\). We can pull some other shenanigans too with changing the speed of the cursor the closer we get to the target and I’ll show the math for that too now itself when the curve math is simple. I’m not super sure how other people do this but my first thought when considering variable speed is writing some dynamics for velocity or acceleration. One simple case is with constant acceleration \(a'\) so that velocity decreases at a constant rate. In the last constant velocity case the velocity vector was \(\left(\frac{s'(x_T - x_0)}{t'},\frac{s'(y_T - y_0)}{t'}\right)\) and in this case we need to determine some initial velocity \((v_{0,x}, v_{0,y})\) and can write the position of the cursor at the i-th update as \((x_0 + i\cdot v_{0,x} + \frac{1}{2}\cdot i^2\cdot \frac{2(x_T - x_0 - v_{0,x}t')}{t'^2}, y_0 + i\cdot v_{0,y} + \frac{1}{2}\cdot i^2\cdot \frac{2(y_T - y_0 - v_{0,y}t')}{t'^2})\). In general though, I don’t think that people move with constant accerlation so it’s probably wise to have some sort of stochastic principle for this acceleration term at each timestep.</p> <p><strong>2. Moving in a sequence of straight lines</strong> Think of this like the more discrete and fine tuned version of moving in a direct line. There are basically two approached, either you write some specific algorithmic manner of diverging away from the target or you do it stochastically but still make sure the path converges to the target. In actual practice, I think there are a few ways one can do this. The first that comes to mind is at each update step to draw a direct line from the current position to the target and place and have some predetermined idea for what percentage of the of the way the cursor will travel based on which i-th update step one is on. Then we preturb this i-th step target coordinate stochastically somehow or even preturb the angle of approach by drawing the pertubations from some distribution with mean zero.</p> <p>The final issue to consider here is the issue of speed. Since we discretize the steps, choosing a different constant speed for each step that decreases the closer we are to the target makes and this simulates having some acceleration. Then again, we can do a similar thing as above and be a bit more random than that.</p> <p>The one issue that I can preemptively see from this approach is cases where you never reach the target or generally taking too far steps away from the target leading to convergence towards the target way too late. People don’t generally overshoot or diverge from their target a crazy amount. Handling this will definitely require some level of calibration of how much randomness should be in the process but I also think it would be wise to make the randomness decrease the closer the cursor is to the target.</p> <p><strong>3. Moving in curves</strong> This is basically the same concept as the previous case except you move in a curve instead of a series of straight lines. There is some math principle called Bézier curves to draw such curves which also happens to be a process that one can imbue a lot of randomness into.</p> <p><strong>4. Considering human behavior</strong> I mentioned a few behaviors above that I personally tend to have when moving my mouse but</p> <p><strong>5. The ML perspective</strong> At the end of the day, there is also the approach of throwing everything into some ML model with a bunch of examples of human made and robot made curves and speeds.</p> <p>All this is interesting to talk about from a ideation perspective but I feel like making some animations or seeing the cursor actually move would be much cooler. It’s a type of project that I am really interested to do for the sake of making something cool but not sure when I’ll get the time. This type of stuff reminds me of what Shane from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/StuffMadeHere">Stuff Made Here</a> does; he gets to work on all these cool projects that one would not usually be able to with a unrelated job.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="miscelaneous-math-fun"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’m currently on a bus to DC for the weekend and have gotten tired on working on econ things for now so here I am talking about this. I had a conversation with work friend last week about CAPTCHA and RECAPTCHA, you know I had to pull the CMU flex and talk about how the guy who made that was a CMU professor and how they managed to make hella money off of it from the New York Times, and the conversation strayed into the general realm of bot detection. He was telling me how for some of the new Google bot detection stuff they track the movement of your cursor when you go to interact with whatever puzzle they give you. The very basic main idea is that humans don’t move in perfect straight lines and “botters” (if that is indeed the adjective to describe them, maybe botists or botmens/botwomans/botpeople) are sometimes too lazy to bother making the cursor move in some more nuanced way. At a higher level even if the botter were to make the cursor move in curves there is still a mathematical difference between a perfect curve and imperfect ones.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">TidyTuesday Week 40</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/TTWeek40/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TidyTuesday Week 40"/><published>2024-10-08T15:24:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-08T15:24:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/TTWeek40</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/TTWeek40/"><![CDATA[<iframe src="/assets/pdf/TidyTuesday_Week40_2024.pdf" width="100%" height="1000px"></iframe>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="tidy-tuesday"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">TidyTuesday Week 39</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/TTWeek39/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TidyTuesday Week 39"/><published>2024-10-01T15:24:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-01T15:24:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/TTWeek39</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/TTWeek39/"><![CDATA[<iframe src="/assets/pdf/TidyTuesday_Week39_2024.pdf" width="100%" height="1000px"></iframe>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="tidy-tuesday"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">airplane networks pt. 1</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/airplane-networks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="airplane networks pt. 1"/><published>2024-09-28T16:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-28T16:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/airplane-networks</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/airplane-networks/"><![CDATA[<p>I have been so unlucky with my flights this year; I haven’t had a trip yet where one of the flights wasn’t either delayed or canceled. The closest I’ve got to a perfect trip was just a few weeks ago where my flight got delayed by 15 mins, but everything else has been by either a couple hours or has been a cancellation. For one of my originally planned trip to Dallas, my flight there got canceled and I never got to catch any other flight to Dallas that weekend because of all the people whose flights got canceled and were then on the stand-by list (there were basically around 100 per flight).</p> <p>This happens to me now mostly because I’m flying from NYC (as opposed to Pittsburgh where the only time I’ve ever had an issue was once when I was flying to … you guessed it, NYC). Specifically, NYC (and Atlanta for that matter) are such big airports in terms of air traffic and interconnectivity with other airports that a small weather delay on one side of the country has drastic ripple effects in NYC since there are missing planes or crews. Maybe I’ve just been at the brunt of a lot of bad luck and we can’t design these airport systems any better but perhaps there’s an interesting question here about how we can do better. Sure there are some unavoidable situations, such as a city being inherently desirable to travel but there are factors that we can control such as how many resources to dedicate to a specific airport or whether or not to connect two airports by a flight path.</p> <p>I’ll go more in detail about how we’ll be representing airline traffic networks and the optimization process in a post in the future but to be able to do the optimization we need to make sure we have a well-defined problem. Specifically, we need some framework of characteristics that are <em>good</em> and a way to classify one traffic network as being better than another. This is by no means an exhaustive list but here are some characteristics that I’ve thought of.</p> <ul> <li>Network A is better than Network B if it costs less.</li> <li>Network A is better than Network B if the closing of one or more airports affects fewer flight routes or flight traffic.</li> <li>Network A is better than Network B if the average flight path duration is less.</li> </ul> <p>To be able to claim a best network, we have to also come up with some relative weightage for how much we value one of these characteristics over another. I’m not going to make any sort of claim on this here just because that gets into more normative questions about which of the above are more important than the others.</p> <p>On one hand, the question of optimizing this network is indeed interesting but I’m also curious about what is the worst that we can do. What would the worst case air traffic network look like? In this case to make sure there is a well-defined problem to solve, we have to also craft a unitary definition for the worst network or a class of <em>bad</em> characteristics and find networks that have all of them. We can consider it to just be the opposite of the <em>good</em> characteristics above, but I’m sure there is another classification that might make more sense based on how we mathematically portray these airline traffic networks. At one edge case it could be a network where no node is connected to another but I don’t think that really qualifies as a legitimate air traffic network so we would also have to apply more restrictions such as ensuring that there is at least one path from each node of the network to another. One other design that I initially think of that could be maximally bad is one where there is one mega airport that connects to every other airport and no other airports have any other connections between eachother. This way, a weather event in the central airport would disrupt travel everywhere, but then again I’m not sure if this is the objective worst.</p> <p>This post is only part one because I did not have the time to fully flesh out the pdf that I wanted to type out. There might be some code in the future there as well although I have no idea how I’m going to have the time generally.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="econ-thoughts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have been so unlucky with my flights this year; I haven’t had a trip yet where one of the flights wasn’t either delayed or canceled. The closest I’ve got to a perfect trip was just a few weeks ago where my flight got delayed by 15 mins, but everything else has been by either a couple hours or has been a cancellation. For one of my originally planned trip to Dallas, my flight there got canceled and I never got to catch any other flight to Dallas that weekend because of all the people whose flights got canceled and were then on the stand-by list (there were basically around 100 per flight).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">TidyTuesday Week 38</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/TTWeek38/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TidyTuesday Week 38"/><published>2024-09-24T15:24:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-24T15:24:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/TTWeek38</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/TTWeek38/"><![CDATA[<iframe src="/assets/pdf/TidyTuesday_Week38_2024.pdf" width="100%" height="1000px"></iframe>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="tidy-tuesday"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">September 21st weekend</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/september21stweekend/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="September 21st weekend"/><published>2024-09-21T23:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-21T23:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/september21stweekend</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/september21stweekend/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been watching this YouTuber recently called <em>Quantum Boy</em>. His videos are poetry to me, both in his video editing style and in how much I relate to him personally. He’s currently a Physics PhD student in Boston, and seeing him explore the city reminded me of the nostalgic and wonder-filled lens through which I viewed the world around me during my early days in Pittsburgh. Maybe it’s the subway heat and grime, but that’s not the way I view New York. It could also be that this lens gets applied with both time and distance, but that’s not something I can tell for a while later. I definitely don’t regret any way that I’ve used my time here so far, but if there is one thing I do regret, it is not developing that sense of attachment to the city. That being said, I may or may not be leaving for a different city in a year, so this is something that I’ll be keeping in mind going into grad school. Outside of that, though, in watching <em>Quantum Boy</em>, I’ve realized that no matter what, the one thing I do want in my new place next year is a blackboard installed into the wall (and some Hagoromo chalk to go with it too).</p> <p>In other news, I went to see a Miami FC vs. New York FC game today. To date, this has been the sporting event with the most energy that I’ve been to, which seems crazy to me given that it is only MLS (Major League Soccer). I’ve always passively had some desire to go to a premier league football game but this experience has pushed that desire to the forefront. I can’t imagine what it would feel like at some Dortmund game (which happens to be the first jersey I’ve ever gotten) with <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f4ipvQ87lKE">a massive tifo in the back</a>.</p> <p>I’m going to close off by addressing the lack of econ in my posts recently. I actually have number of drafts in the making but finding the time to write each post to my personal satisfaction is quite difficult right now amidst grad apps and NSF. I will say, though, that there are quite a few bangers in store so be on the lookout for those for whenever I get the time to be able to flesh them out. The one enormous victory I’ve had in terms of finishing a project is TidyTuesday. I know I said that I would have it up a lot earlier but I hadn’t finished the latex automated report building by then and the thought of having to latex everything in a nicely formatted manner only to have to redo it while writing python code to write in latex disgusted me so I put it off for a while.</p> <p>I’ve managed to finally finish the latex automation last Wednesday so I’ve been cooking up these random regressions for the past handful of days to prep a post this coming Tuesday. Since I have to do minimal work for TidyTuesday going forward, get ready to finally see posts every Tuesday (even while apps are going on). I’ve talked about what my TidyTuesday project is a few times before but I feel the need to explain again in each new post about it. Basically it is a repo that takes two random datasets every day from some API, runs a linear regression, and then creates a plot, regression table, and writes some paragraphs explaining each of the time series used in the regression. So far I only pull data using the FRED API (and yes I mean FRED (Federal Reserve Economic Data) instead of FED, I’ve had some questions about this) but I’ve been working with the Bureau of Economic Analysis (BEA) and Bureau of Labor Statistics (BLS) APIs as well recently so that’s a next step. One other next step is making my regressions smarter in a way that doesn’t require me to actively do work. In other words, running linear regressions between random datasets doesn’t usually really yield any beneficial insight but often times this is also because the relationship between any given two series can be non-linear or there are some obvious confounding variables that delegitimizes any insight we could glean. Time series especially often times detrended when regressing which is not something that I am currently doing. Building out this aspect of the code is a bit more nuanced of a problem; I have a few ideas in mind such as keeping a list of all the various regression techniques and choosing whichever one fares the best (by some metric that I decide) or even asking some chat gpt like AI for its recommendation on what type of regression to run and just running that. Regardless, this is a problem for future Pranay who is already done with his applications but I’m curious about the potential of this idea.</p> <p>I don’t have any underlying purpose driving this TidyTuesday project other than it seemed like something interesting to do at the time and recently I’ve been feeling like that is something missing from academia (at least in econ). Not to say that pursuing research problems with a strong motivation or <em>noble</em> purpose is wrong, I just feel like doing something just for the sake of it being an interesting problem to consider should be more normalized.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal-updates"/><category term="tidy-tuesday"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve been watching this YouTuber recently called Quantum Boy. His videos are poetry to me, both in his video editing style and in how much I relate to him personally. He’s currently a Physics PhD student in Boston, and seeing him explore the city reminded me of the nostalgic and wonder-filled lens through which I viewed the world around me during my early days in Pittsburgh. Maybe it’s the subway heat and grime, but that’s not the way I view New York. It could also be that this lens gets applied with both time and distance, but that’s not something I can tell for a while later. I definitely don’t regret any way that I’ve used my time here so far, but if there is one thing I do regret, it is not developing that sense of attachment to the city. That being said, I may or may not be leaving for a different city in a year, so this is something that I’ll be keeping in mind going into grad school. Outside of that, though, in watching Quantum Boy, I’ve realized that no matter what, the one thing I do want in my new place next year is a blackboard installed into the wall (and some Hagoromo chalk to go with it too).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">things i find boring</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/boredom/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="things i find boring"/><published>2024-09-06T22:50:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-06T22:50:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/boredom</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/boredom/"><![CDATA[<p>My headphones are in a really dire situation. They’re wireless and so when I lost one of the pairs a few months ago I tried to manage with just the right piece. I’m constantly scared that taking the subway everyday, with its loud noises, is going to render me deaf eventually, so I really value the noise canceling; riding the subway with just the right headphone was a game of angling the right side of my head towards the sounds. Since then, the situation has deteriorated further and my remaining headphone piece is now broken, which makes my subway daily commutes completely headphoneless. This is quite boring, to say the least. No more podcasts, no more music, no more isolating myself in a bubble of noise canceling. I’m usually an avid people watcher — at least in public situations where that’s not awkward — but that’s not something you can do on a subway. If you happen to make awkward eye contact with someone its not like you just walk past each other, you’re going to have to sit right across from them for a decent while.</p> <p>I feel like my writing is pretty boring. Rather, to be specific, my writing is boring to those who don’t get excited by the same sorts of econ questions or coding projects as I do which I’ve discovered — now that I have left CMU — is a far smaller population than I previously thought. I’ve done this blog more so for myself, and as an outlet to put some of the econ thoughts in my head on paper so I don’t particularly care if what I write is the most engaging thing on the planet or not but the other day but the other day a friend (and fellow blog reader), showed me another <a href="https://splishsplash.online/p/towards-understanding">blog post</a> that captured me so much even though it had nothing to do with anything that I’m usually interested with. I’ve also been reading a handful of other economists’ blogs and I’ve come to the conclusion that even beyond being a good, economist I want to also be a good communicator. So now I am inspired to focus on not only what I am saying but also how I am saying it.</p> <p>That being said, there is no way I could close off a post without talking about something econ-related. Something that is so pervasive of an issue in macro economics is solving macro models where the state space (the matrix of basic information about the world that the model has to keep track of) is large. In short, it’s quite difficult to build interestingly nuanced models because we are always limited by this fact. I personally find this to be such a boring issue; it’s not an issue of writing a better defined model or one of finding some new mechanism but just that there are too many things to keep track of. The research into finding ways to solve these large dimensional state space systems does seem interesting but the problem itself seems so blunt and dull.</p> <p>Regardless, I actually strongly believe that regularly being bored for bouts of time throughout the week really draws out one’s creativity. I’m not anti-technology, but I do believe that the creative part of people’s minds is something that is less exercised nowadays given the trend of constant stimulus and content aimed at short attention spans. That being said, I don’t think that sitting in one place and mindlessly staring into the sky is exercising this creative muscle (there is a different time and place for meditative practice), but to properly exercise, one has to actively put themselves in a scenario with little stimulus and start imagining what they want. The reason why I started this blog was because I wanted a place to formalize all those random subway thoughts that come to mind when I’m sitting there bored out of my mind. One distinction that I did want to make before I close is the difference between being bored and doing something that is boring. Although doing something boring may indeed be important, I don’t think this is actively beneficial for flexing those creativity muscles.</p> <p><em>This post was a little bit different from the others I’ve done so far just thematically. I’ve never thought of myself as a writer per se and still don’t, but I think it is a skill that I want to actively work on going into the future, so you may see many different types of posts to come.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal-updates"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My headphones are in a really dire situation. They’re wireless and so when I lost one of the pairs a few months ago I tried to manage with just the right piece. I’m constantly scared that taking the subway everyday, with its loud noises, is going to render me deaf eventually, so I really value the noise canceling; riding the subway with just the right headphone was a game of angling the right side of my head towards the sounds. Since then, the situation has deteriorated further and my remaining headphone piece is now broken, which makes my subway daily commutes completely headphoneless. This is quite boring, to say the least. No more podcasts, no more music, no more isolating myself in a bubble of noise canceling. I’m usually an avid people watcher — at least in public situations where that’s not awkward — but that’s not something you can do on a subway. If you happen to make awkward eye contact with someone its not like you just walk past each other, you’re going to have to sit right across from them for a decent while.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">labor day weekend</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/labor-day-weekend/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="labor day weekend"/><published>2024-08-31T19:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-31T19:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/labor-day-weekend</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/labor-day-weekend/"><![CDATA[<p>The pressure from all the upcoming deadlines is really rearing its head now. I personally find it best to just set my mind to focus on one thing at a time; for example, during college, I could just set out an order in which to do all the problem sets I had and just focus solely on each one until they were done. However, I think that strategy does not bode well in a situation where I have to do my normal Fed work, NSF, GRE, etc. It’s not the worst; it’s just that I have to get really good at shifting modalities, but I’ve been slowly getting better at it.</p> <p>I did promise a follow-up post to last week’s discussion of modeling politician decision-making, and that is still being worked on, but I have a few other things I need to focus on, so that will have to be postponed for a later week. I did want to say, though, that there are quite a few addenda that need to be added to make sure I’m being satisfactorily accurate and descriptive.</p> <p>In other news, this long weekend is quite well needed. I’ve been told that I usually say that even if I don’t do much each weekend, I actually do get around, and I’ll finally be going to a play (Harry Potter and the Cursed Child). This week I also finally managed to go to <a href="https://birdbox.nyc/">Birdbox</a>, and it is indeed quite good. It does not, however, take the spot as my favorite fried chicken sandwich. It is definitely number two, but the flavors in a Rowdy Rooster sandwich just hit differently (it’s probably the Indian in me).</p> <p>Short post this week since I’m grinding NSF and GRE prep. Until next week!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal-updates"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The pressure from all the upcoming deadlines is really rearing its head now. I personally find it best to just set my mind to focus on one thing at a time; for example, during college, I could just set out an order in which to do all the problem sets I had and just focus solely on each one until they were done. However, I think that strategy does not bode well in a situation where I have to do my normal Fed work, NSF, GRE, etc. It’s not the worst; it’s just that I have to get really good at shifting modalities, but I’ve been slowly getting better at it.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the dynamics of incumbent politicians pt. 1</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/dynamics-of-politicians/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the dynamics of incumbent politicians pt. 1"/><published>2024-08-26T22:05:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-26T22:05:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/dynamics-of-politicians</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/dynamics-of-politicians/"><![CDATA[<p>I went to a Stephen Colbert show recently (you can actually see me in a few of the audience shots), and all things considered, it was quite an interesting experience. Everything is very streamlined (it makes sense given that they have a lot of practice with it), down to even the bathroom breaks. They do a lot of encouraging the audience to have big reactions to jokes or guests coming on stage, which is something that I expected, but being in the audience live gives you a different sense of responsibility for enriching the experience of the TV audience.</p> <p>Otherwise, it was a lot more political than I remember it being, which in retrospect does make sense given the upcoming presidential election. I don’t remember being this inundated with political content last election cycle, despite living in a more swing state than NY, but I’m seeing political content everywhere now, especially on YouTube.</p> <p>As an aside, I was rewatching Oppenheimer a couple of weeks ago (which, as another aside, has taken the place of my favorite movie of all time, a spot I could not definitively fill until Oppenheimer. I am truly so sad that I could not watch it in theaters) and realized how different the politicians seemed in that age compared to my perception of politicians now (on either side of the aisle, to be honest). They just seemed so much smarter and more calculated rather than just spouting random brazen comments all willy-nilly. I feel the term “career politician” has been cast aside as an undesired trait in the past few election cycles, but I think that there may be a shift back towards “the swamp” in the sense of the intelligence and an all-around put-togetherness of our candidates. Right now, Pete Buttigieg strikes me as the most put-together politician who does think deeply about policy issues and is able to convey the depth of his thought publicly as well, but maybe there are a lot of people like this that I don’t know about because I’m not that much into politics. I don’t know too much about John McCain, but I’ve been seeing quite a few videos about him on my YouTube feed recently, and it reminded me of a different class of politicians who held high certain virtues which distance them from the current “Trumpism” effect.</p> <p>Amidst that, it’s interesting to see how old Republican politicians who have acted in very different ways have turned to embrace the new Trump-era tactics and think about the incentive structure that leads them to so rapidly adopt the new regime.</p> <p>All this has brought me back to this day last year when I was thinking generally about politics and what the incentives that dictate the way politicians act as they do are. Back then, I never really arrived at something that motivated me to make a full-fledged post. I’ve now since revisited the question, and it took me a little bit, but I think I’ve been able to put something together to model the behavior of politicians in a neat way. So with that said, before I close off for you to get into the PDF (although I’m in Markdown now with the new website, doing the LaTeX separately for the most part is still much better), this topic will be a two-post series. Today I first talk about the model in depth, and next week I’ll try to get my in-page Jupyter notebook feature working for you all to see some code to make some pretty visuals and see how one would address this question empirically.</p> <iframe src="/assets/pdf/incumbent-politicians.pdf" width="100%" height="1000px"></iframe>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="econ-thoughts"/><category term="personal-updates"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I went to a Stephen Colbert show recently (you can actually see me in a few of the audience shots), and all things considered, it was quite an interesting experience. Everything is very streamlined (it makes sense given that they have a lot of practice with it), down to even the bathroom breaks. They do a lot of encouraging the audience to have big reactions to jokes or guests coming on stage, which is something that I expected, but being in the audience live gives you a different sense of responsibility for enriching the experience of the TV audience.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Brief TidyTuesday Update</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/TTupdate/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Brief TidyTuesday Update"/><published>2024-08-20T07:38:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-20T07:38:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/TTupdate</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/TTupdate/"><![CDATA[<p>There was supposed to be a post up today and I do indeed have all the materials prepped for this, but I am still trying to mess around with the latex report generation and the best way to format everything so I’m gonna have to wait till next week to do the first post of the refurbished series.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="tidy-tuesday"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There was supposed to be a post up today and I do indeed have all the materials prepped for this, but I am still trying to mess around with the latex report generation and the best way to format everything so I’m gonna have to wait till next week to do the first post of the refurbished series.]]></summary></entry></feed>