<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-09-28T21:23:11+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Pranay Gundam</title><entry><title type="html">airplane networks pt. 1</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/airplane-networks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="airplane networks pt. 1"/><published>2024-09-28T16:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-28T16:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/airplane-networks</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/airplane-networks/"><![CDATA[<p>I have been so unlucky with my flights this year; I haven’t had a trip yet where one of the flights wasn’t either delayed or canceled. The closest I’ve got to a perfect trip was just a few weeks ago where my flight got delayed by 15 mins, but everything else has been by either a couple hours or has been a cancellation. For one of my originally planned trip to Dallas, my flight there got canceled and I never got to catch any other flight to Dallas that weekend because of all the people whose flights got canceled and were then on the stand-by list (there were basically around 100 per flight).</p> <p>This happens to me now mostly because I’m flying from NYC (as opposed to Pittsburgh where the only time I’ve ever had an issue was once when I was flying to … you guessed it, NYC). Specifically, NYC (and Atlanta for that matter) are such big airports in terms of air traffic and interconnectivity with other airports that a small weather delay on one side of the country has drastic ripple effects in NYC since there are missing planes or crews. Maybe I’ve just been at the brunt of a lot of bad luck and we can’t design these airport systems any better but perhaps there’s an interesting question here about how we can do better. Sure there are some unavoidable situations, such as a city being inherently desirable to travel but there are factors that we can control such as how many resources to dedicate to a specific airport or whether or not to connect two airports by a flight path.</p> <p>I’ll go more in detail about how we’ll be representing airline traffic networks and the optimization process in a post in the future but to be able to do the optimization we need to make sure we have a well-defined problem. Specifically, we need some framework of characteristics that are <em>good</em> and a way to classify one traffic network as being better than another. This is by no means an exhaustive list but here are some characteristics that I’ve thought of.</p> <ul> <li>Network A is better than Network B if it costs less.</li> <li>Network A is better than Network B if the closing of one or more airports affects fewer flight routes or flight traffic.</li> <li>Network A is better than Network B if the average flight path duration is less.</li> </ul> <p>To be able to claim a best network, we have to also come up with some relative weightage for how much we value one of these characteristics over another. I’m not going to make any sort of claim on this here just because that gets into more normative questions about which of the above are more important than the others.</p> <p>On one hand, the question of optimizing this network is indeed interesting but I’m also curious about what is the worst that we can do. What would the worst case air traffic network look like? In this case to make sure there is a well-defined problem to solve, we have to also craft a unitary definition for the worst network or a class of <em>bad</em> characteristics and find networks that have all of them. We can consider it to just be the opposite of the <em>good</em> characteristics above, but I’m sure there is another classification that might make more sense based on how we mathematically portray these airline traffic networks. At one edge case it could be a network where no node is connected to another but I don’t think that really qualifies as a legitimate air traffic network so we would also have to apply more restrictions such as ensuring that there is at least one path from each node of the network to another. One other design that I initially think of that could be maximally bad is one where there is one mega airport that connects to every other airport and no other airports have any other connections between eachother. This way, a weather event in the central airport would disrupt travel everywhere, but then again I’m not sure if this is the objective worst.</p> <p>This post is only part one because I did not have the time to fully flesh out the pdf that I wanted to type out. There might be some code in the future there as well although I have no idea how I’m going to have the time generally.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="econ-thoughts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have been so unlucky with my flights this year; I haven’t had a trip yet where one of the flights wasn’t either delayed or canceled. The closest I’ve got to a perfect trip was just a few weeks ago where my flight got delayed by 15 mins, but everything else has been by either a couple hours or has been a cancellation. For one of my originally planned trip to Dallas, my flight there got canceled and I never got to catch any other flight to Dallas that weekend because of all the people whose flights got canceled and were then on the stand-by list (there were basically around 100 per flight).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tidy Tuesday, Week 38, 2024</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/TT2024week38/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tidy Tuesday, Week 38, 2024"/><published>2024-09-24T19:38:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-24T19:38:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/TT2024week38</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/TT2024week38/"><![CDATA[<p>First one up!</p> <iframe src="/assets/pdf/TidyTuesday_2024_week38.pdf" width="100%" height="1000px"></iframe>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="tidy-tuesday"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[First one up!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">September 21st weekend</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/september21stweekend/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="September 21st weekend"/><published>2024-09-21T23:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-21T23:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/september21stweekend</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/september21stweekend/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been watching this YouTuber recently called <em>Quantum Boy</em>. His videos are like poetry to me, both in his video editing style and in how much I relate to him personally. He’s currently a Physics PhD student in Boston, and seeing him explore the city reminded me of the nostalgic and wonder-filled lens through which I viewed the world around me during my early days in Pittsburgh. Maybe it’s the subway heat and grime, but that’s not the way I view New York. It could also be that this lens gets applied with both time and distance, but that’s not something I can tell for a while later. I definitely don’t regret any way that I’ve used my time here so far, but if there is one thing I do regret, it is not developing that sense of attachment to the city. That being said, I may or may not be leaving for a different city in a year, so this is something that I’ll be keeping in mind going into grad school. Outside of that, though, in watching <em>Quantum Boy</em>, I’ve realized that no matter what, the one thing I do want in my new place next year is a blackboard installed into the wall (and some Hagoromo chalk to go with it too).</p> <p>In other news, I went to see a Miami FC vs. New York FC game today. To date, this has been the sporting event with the most energy that I’ve been to, which seems crazy to me given that it is only MLS (Major League Soccer). I’ve always passively had some desire to go to a premier league football game but this experience has pushed that desire to the forefront. I can’t imagine what it would feel like at some Dortmund game (which happens to be the first jersey I’ve ever gotten) with <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f4ipvQ87lKE">a massive tifo in the back</a>.</p> <p>I’m going to close off by addressing the lack of econ in my posts recently. I actually have a number of drafts in the making but finding the time to write each post to my personal satisfaction is quite difficult right now amidst grad apps and NSF. I will say, though, that there are quite a few bangers in store so be on the lookout for those for whenever I get the time to be able to flesh them out. The one enormous victory I’ve had in terms of finishing a project, however, is TidyTuesday. I know I said that I would have it up a lot earlier but I hadn’t finished the latex automated report building by then and the thought of having to latex everything in a nicely formatted manner only to have to redo it while writing python code to write in latex disgusted me so I put it off for a while.</p> <p>I’ve managed to finally finish the latex automation last Wednesday so I’ve been cooking up these random regressions for the past handful of days to prep a post this coming Tuesday. Since I have to do minimal work for TidyTuesday going forward, get ready to finally see posts every Tuesday (even while apps are going on). I’ve talked about what my TidyTuesday project is a few times before but I feel the need to explain again in each new post about it. Basically it is a repo that takes two random datasets every day from some API, runs a linear regression, and then creates a plot, regression table, and writes some paragraphs explaining each of the time series used in the regression. So far I only pull data using the FRED API (and yes I mean FRED (Federal Reserve Economic Data) instead of FED, I’ve had some questions about this) but I’ve been working with the Bureau of Economic Analysis (BEA) and Bureau of Labor Statistics (BLS) APIs as well recently so that’s a next step. One other next step is making my regressions smarter in a way that doesn’t require me to actively do work. In other words, running linear regressions between random datasets doesn’t usually really yield any beneficial insight but often times this is also because the relationship between any given two series can be non-linear or there are some obvious confounding variables that delegitimizes any insight we could glean. For time series especially, one often times detrends when creating models which is not something that I am currently doing. Building out this aspect of the code is a bit more nuanced of a problem; I have a few ideas in mind such as keeping a list of all the various regression techniques and choosing whichever one fares the best (by some metric that I decide) or even asking some chat gpt like AI for its recommendation on what type of regression to run and just running that. Regardless, this is a problem for future Pranay who is already done with his applications but I’m curious about the potential of this idea.</p> <p>I don’t have any underlying purpose driving this TidyTuesday project other than it seemed like something interesting to do at the time and recently I’ve been feeling like that is something missing from academia (at least in econ). Not to say that pursuing research problems with a strong motivation or <em>noble</em> purpose is wrong, I just feel like doing something just for the sake of it being an interesting problem to consider should be more acceptable.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal-updates"/><category term="tidy-tuesday"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve been watching this YouTuber recently called Quantum Boy. His videos are like poetry to me, both in his video editing style and in how much I relate to him personally. He’s currently a Physics PhD student in Boston, and seeing him explore the city reminded me of the nostalgic and wonder-filled lens through which I viewed the world around me during my early days in Pittsburgh. Maybe it’s the subway heat and grime, but that’s not the way I view New York. It could also be that this lens gets applied with both time and distance, but that’s not something I can tell for a while later. I definitely don’t regret any way that I’ve used my time here so far, but if there is one thing I do regret, it is not developing that sense of attachment to the city. That being said, I may or may not be leaving for a different city in a year, so this is something that I’ll be keeping in mind going into grad school. Outside of that, though, in watching Quantum Boy, I’ve realized that no matter what, the one thing I do want in my new place next year is a blackboard installed into the wall (and some Hagoromo chalk to go with it too).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">things i find boring</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/boredom/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="things i find boring"/><published>2024-09-06T22:50:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-06T22:50:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/boredom</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/boredom/"><![CDATA[<p>My headphones are in a really dire situation. They’re wireless and so when I lost one of the pairs a few months ago I tried to manage with just the right piece. I’m constantly scared that taking the subway everyday, with its loud noises, is going to render me deaf eventually, so I really value the noise canceling; riding the subway with just the right headphone was a game of angling the right side of my head towards the sounds. Since then, the situation has deteriorated further and my remaining headphone piece is now broken, which makes my subway daily commutes completely headphoneless. This is quite boring, to say the least. No more podcasts, no more music, no more isolating myself in a bubble of noise canceling. I’m usually an avid people watcher — at least in public situations where that’s not awkward — but that’s not something you can do on a subway. If you happen to make awkward eye contact with someone its not like you just walk past each other, you’re going to have to sit right across from them for a decent while.</p> <p>I feel like my writing is pretty boring. Rather, to be specific, my writing is boring to those who don’t get excited by the same sorts of econ questions or coding projects as I do which I’ve discovered — now that I have left CMU — is a far smaller population than I previously thought. I’ve done this blog more so for myself, and as an outlet to put some of the econ thoughts in my head on paper so I don’t particularly care if what I write is the most engaging thing on the planet or not but the other day but the other day a friend (and fellow blog reader), showed me another <a href="https://splishsplash.online/p/towards-understanding">blog post</a> that captured me so much even though it had nothing to do with anything that I’m usually interested with. I’ve also been reading a handful of other economists’ blogs and I’ve come to the conclusion that even beyond being a good, economist I want to also be a good communicator. So now I am inspired to focus on not only what I am saying but also how I am saying it.</p> <p>That being said, there is no way I could close off a post without talking about something econ-related. Something that is so pervasive of an issue in macro economics is solving macro models where the state space (the matrix of basic information about the world that the model has to keep track of) is large. In short, it’s quite difficult to build interestingly nuanced models because we are always limited by this fact. I personally find this to be such a boring issue; it’s not an issue of writing a better defined model or one of finding some new mechanism but just that there are too many things to keep track of. The research into finding ways to solve these large dimensional state space systems does seem interesting but the problem itself seems so blunt and dull.</p> <p>Regardless, I actually strongly believe that regularly being bored for bouts of time throughout the week really draws out one’s creativity. I’m not anti-technology, but I do believe that the creative part of people’s minds is something that is less exercised nowadays given the trend of constant stimulus and content aimed at short attention spans. That being said, I don’t think that sitting in one place and mindlessly staring into the sky is exercising this creative muscle (there is a different time and place for meditative practice), but to properly exercise, one has to actively put themselves in a scenario with little stimulus and start imagining what they want. The reason why I started this blog was because I wanted a place to formalize all those random subway thoughts that come to mind when I’m sitting there bored out of my mind. One distinction that I did want to make before I close is the difference between being bored and doing something that is boring. Although doing something boring may indeed be important, I don’t think this is actively beneficial for flexing those creativity muscles.</p> <p><em>This post was a little bit different from the others I’ve done so far just thematically. I’ve never thought of myself as a writer per se and still don’t, but I think it is a skill that I want to actively work on going into the future, so you may see many different types of posts to come.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal-updates"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My headphones are in a really dire situation. They’re wireless and so when I lost one of the pairs a few months ago I tried to manage with just the right piece. I’m constantly scared that taking the subway everyday, with its loud noises, is going to render me deaf eventually, so I really value the noise canceling; riding the subway with just the right headphone was a game of angling the right side of my head towards the sounds. Since then, the situation has deteriorated further and my remaining headphone piece is now broken, which makes my subway daily commutes completely headphoneless. This is quite boring, to say the least. No more podcasts, no more music, no more isolating myself in a bubble of noise canceling. I’m usually an avid people watcher — at least in public situations where that’s not awkward — but that’s not something you can do on a subway. If you happen to make awkward eye contact with someone its not like you just walk past each other, you’re going to have to sit right across from them for a decent while.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">labor day weekend</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/labor-day-weekend/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="labor day weekend"/><published>2024-08-31T19:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-31T19:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/labor-day-weekend</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/labor-day-weekend/"><![CDATA[<p>The pressure from all the upcoming deadlines is really rearing its head now. I personally find it best to just set my mind to focus on one thing at a time; for example, during college, I could just set out an order in which to do all the problem sets I had and just focus solely on each one until they were done. However, I think that strategy does not bode well in a situation where I have to do my normal Fed work, NSF, GRE, etc. It’s not the worst; it’s just that I have to get really good at shifting modalities, but I’ve been slowly getting better at it.</p> <p>I did promise a follow-up post to last week’s discussion of modeling politician decision-making, and that is still being worked on, but I have a few other things I need to focus on, so that will have to be postponed for a later week. I did want to say, though, that there are quite a few addenda that need to be added to make sure I’m being satisfactorily accurate and descriptive.</p> <p>In other news, this long weekend is quite well needed. I’ve been told that I usually say that even if I don’t do much each weekend, I actually do get around, and I’ll finally be going to a play (Harry Potter and the Cursed Child). This week I also finally managed to go to <a href="https://birdbox.nyc/">Birdbox</a>, and it is indeed quite good. It does not, however, take the spot as my favorite fried chicken sandwich. It is definitely number two, but the flavors in a Rowdy Rooster sandwich just hit differently (it’s probably the Indian in me).</p> <p>Short post this week since I’m grinding NSF and GRE prep. Until next week!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal-updates"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The pressure from all the upcoming deadlines is really rearing its head now. I personally find it best to just set my mind to focus on one thing at a time; for example, during college, I could just set out an order in which to do all the problem sets I had and just focus solely on each one until they were done. However, I think that strategy does not bode well in a situation where I have to do my normal Fed work, NSF, GRE, etc. It’s not the worst; it’s just that I have to get really good at shifting modalities, but I’ve been slowly getting better at it.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the dynamics of incumbent politicians pt. 1</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/dynamics-of-politicians/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the dynamics of incumbent politicians pt. 1"/><published>2024-08-26T22:05:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-26T22:05:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/dynamics-of-politicians</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/dynamics-of-politicians/"><![CDATA[<p>I went to a Stephen Colbert show recently (you can actually see me in a few of the audience shots), and all things considered, it was quite an interesting experience. Everything is very streamlined (it makes sense given that they have a lot of practice with it), down to even the bathroom breaks. They do a lot of encouraging the audience to have big reactions to jokes or guests coming on stage, which is something that I expected, but being in the audience live gives you a different sense of responsibility for enriching the experience of the TV audience.</p> <p>Otherwise, it was a lot more political than I remember it being, which in retrospect does make sense given the upcoming presidential election. I don’t remember being this inundated with political content last election cycle, despite living in a more swing state than NY, but I’m seeing political content everywhere now, especially on YouTube.</p> <p>As an aside, I was rewatching Oppenheimer a couple of weeks ago (which, as another aside, has taken the place of my favorite movie of all time, a spot I could not definitively fill until Oppenheimer. I am truly so sad that I could not watch it in theaters) and realized how different the politicians seemed in that age compared to my perception of politicians now (on either side of the aisle, to be honest). They just seemed so much smarter and more calculated rather than just spouting random brazen comments all willy-nilly. I feel the term “career politician” has been cast aside as an undesired trait in the past few election cycles, but I think that there may be a shift back towards “the swamp” in the sense of the intelligence and an all-around put-togetherness of our candidates. Right now, Pete Buttigieg strikes me as the most put-together politician who does think deeply about policy issues and is able to convey the depth of his thought publicly as well, but maybe there are a lot of people like this that I don’t know about because I’m not that much into politics. I don’t know too much about John McCain, but I’ve been seeing quite a few videos about him on my YouTube feed recently, and it reminded me of a different class of politicians who held high certain virtues which distance them from the current “Trumpism” effect.</p> <p>Amidst that, it’s interesting to see how old Republican politicians who have acted in very different ways have turned to embrace the new Trump-era tactics and think about the incentive structure that leads them to so rapidly adopt the new regime.</p> <p>All this has brought me back to this day last year when I was thinking generally about politics and what the incentives that dictate the way politicians act as they do are. Back then, I never really arrived at something that motivated me to make a full-fledged post. I’ve now since revisited the question, and it took me a little bit, but I think I’ve been able to put something together to model the behavior of politicians in a neat way. So with that said, before I close off for you to get into the PDF (although I’m in Markdown now with the new website, doing the LaTeX separately for the most part is still much better), this topic will be a two-post series. Today I first talk about the model in depth, and next week I’ll try to get my in-page Jupyter notebook feature working for you all to see some code to make some pretty visuals and see how one would address this question empirically.</p> <iframe src="/assets/pdf/incumbent-politicians.pdf" width="100%" height="1000px"></iframe>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="econ-thoughts"/><category term="personal-updates"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I went to a Stephen Colbert show recently (you can actually see me in a few of the audience shots), and all things considered, it was quite an interesting experience. Everything is very streamlined (it makes sense given that they have a lot of practice with it), down to even the bathroom breaks. They do a lot of encouraging the audience to have big reactions to jokes or guests coming on stage, which is something that I expected, but being in the audience live gives you a different sense of responsibility for enriching the experience of the TV audience.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Brief TidyTuesday Update</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/TTupdate/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Brief TidyTuesday Update"/><published>2024-08-20T07:38:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-20T07:38:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/TTupdate</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/TTupdate/"><![CDATA[<p>There was supposed to be a post up today and I do indeed have all the materials prepped for this, but I am still trying to mess around with the latex report generation and the best way to format everything so I’m gonna have to wait till next week to do the first post of the refurbished series.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="tidy-tuesday"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There was supposed to be a post up today and I do indeed have all the materials prepped for this, but I am still trying to mess around with the latex report generation and the best way to format everything so I’m gonna have to wait till next week to do the first post of the refurbished series.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">spatial models update and stanning for github copilot</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/github-copilot-fan-post/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="spatial models update and stanning for github copilot"/><published>2024-08-17T19:10:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-17T19:10:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/github-copilot-fan-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/github-copilot-fan-post/"><![CDATA[<p>I wanted to start off by saying that Github Co-Pilot is amazing. I’m not super sure about the specifics of what it trains on but it has to somehow look at my git tracked code and give suggestions based on my coding style which is just spectacular. Often times the most demoralizing part of doing a coding project is typing out tedious code that one knows how to write but just takes effort and unnessary mental energy (especially if there are some unintended bugs). Co-Pilot bypasses all of that with just one keystroke; more often than not the code that Co-Pilot writes is not buggy (especially if it’s something not particularly complicated). The greatest thing is that sure you can ask write out a detailed prompt in the chat window for AI to interpret and answer, but Co-Pilot also has an autocomplete feature where you can only write out the name of the function and it does the rest for you (sometimes it even knows what function you want to write next before you type out the name).</p> <p>Then also, before I get into the spatial stuff, one update on <a href="https://github.com/pranay-gundam/TidyTuesday">TidyTuesday</a>. The code is still a work in progress; I still need to get it to a state where I’m satisfied enough to not touch it for a while. That being said, it is currently functional. Meaning I can go on with my TidyTuesday blog series plans but there’s still a little to be done to make it fully automated and also include data from more than just Fred.</p> <p>With those two things out of the way, I want to talk a little about spatial econ. I’m not really sure what it is about spatial models that really captures me. If I were to guess, I know I have had somewhat of an interest in the movement of peoples and how they organize in the context of a city for a while since highschool and it was this interest that leaned me towards doing something spatial related for my senior thesis which has then kept me interested in the field.</p> <p>Before I learned a lot of macro, however, I used to think that there was something intrinsically different between the model written in the spatial literature and those in the general macro setting. This may be just from ignorance of not knowing the general questions that a macro model uses to motivate itself, but in my involvement in the spatial literature thus far I have realized that the inherent motivation is very similar: households making a selection from some choice set to maximize their utility given some budget constraints that introduce unique mechanics. There are few key components of a spatial general equilibrium models that I’ve found are the key marked differences between the two:</p> <ul> <li>The choice set for households (also firms as well for models that include those) is expanded to choosing places to live (and work). Models can differ vastly in terms of when these choices are made or restrictions on how such a choice is made but the commuting costs of households and goods is what gives birth to the rich spatial dynamics that relate the model to reality.</li> <li>Location (blocks) have unique characteristics (which can be anything from natural landmarks to the vibes of a neighborhood) that are incorporated into the model in various ways <ul> <li>Household preferences for these characteristics</li> <li>local productivity shocks and spillover effects</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>These two differences are what drive the unique analysis that we can do with spatial models. For example, we can look at how the migration flows (either people moving their residence or working location) change in response to a local productivity shock, or we can see the extent of the effect that local spillovers have on the composition of households in a location. This may seem a bit abstract to those non-macroeconomics readers in terms of the mechanics of the math, so let’s dive into some more specifics.</p> <p>At its core, a structural macro model is built on connecting the optimization problems of various groups of different types of agents. For the toy model we are building now:</p> <ul> <li>There is a discount factor \(\beta \in (0,1)\) and capital depreciation rate \(\delta \in [0,1]\).</li> <li>Let there be \(N\) many location blocks in which households choose to live and work. Each location also has a living amenity rate \(A_i\) which factors into a household’s utility function.</li> <li>A household is an agent who lives forever and faces the main problem of choosing how much of a good to consume at each point in time \(c_t\), how much time to spend on leisure \(l_t\) instead of working, and which location blocks \(i\) and \(j\) to live and work in respectively (they have to pay a commuting fee \(d_{i,j}\) for every time period based on the chosen \(i\) and \(j\)). Households also have the ability to save from time period to time period and these savings affect (this very nebulous and confusing concept to those not in econ that we call) capital \(k_t\).</li> <li>There are no firms in this world; rather, households “make money” using a production function \(Z_{i_t}\cdot F(k_t, 1 - l_t)\) which uses some function \(F\) to relate how much a household produces based on how much capital they possess and how much time they spend working instead of as leisure time. The \(Z_{i_t}\) is a location-specific random process that all have different means and variances that the households are not sure about, so that one’s working location has an effect on how much they are able to produce: since the process is different for each location, each location has different shocks as well. <ul> <li>This is where I’m making the spatial model “interesting”. The model isn’t just incorporating the spatial component by making households choose where they want to live and work based on which is the best place to live in terms of the amenities and distance to work but also which has good future prospects for location productivity.</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>Specifically, the households solve the following optimization problem \(\max_{c_t, l_t, i_t, j_t} \sum_{t=0}^\infty \beta^t u(c_t, l_t, A_{i_t})\) subject to constraints \(c_t + d_{i_t, j_t} + s_t \leq Z_{i_t}\cdot F(k_t, 1 - l_t)\) to dictate the production/saving and \(k_{t+1} = \delta k_t + s_t\) to dictate the capital.</p> <p>It took me a bit of training to be able to do this, but from the problem statement above you can already paint a qualitative picture of the push and pull that affects the households. They want to choose a location to live in with high location amenities, but they also want it to be close to their work, and they also want to choose a place to work that they think has good prospects for its productivity that factors into the households’ production function (their way of making money). They can also turn the levers of how they make money by saving money for the future to build up their capital. There’s a lot going on already without adding too much complexity; don’t get me started on how to solve and estimate these models.</p> <p>There are plenty more features we can build into this to make it more interesting or realistic, such as introducing firms, government agents, or some intrinsic heterogeneity between households; for example, some households can have low levels of education while others can have higher, which affects their respective production functions and may influence their migratory decisions. My NSF proposal will likely tinker with a couple of these “bonus” features and study them in the context of government policy and their spatial implications.</p> <p>Of course, not even I would say that the model we built above is consistent with reality, and even if we were to relax a few assumptions, we would still be nowhere close. This brings me to a point of economic maturity that I’ve come to learn over the past year. Very rarely in econ are people who are doing these structural models caught up with trying to replicate reality; it is more about exploring the relative effects of some channels on others that is what is interesting in monetary policy research. As always, my blog posts are very stream-of-consciousness and more so a personal outlet for me to espouse some thoughts, so I’m not sure how coherent any of the above is to an outside reader. If you want to know more or are confused (most people reading probably know me in real life, so texting is also good 😊).</p> <p>So to close off, the NSF application is coming along and will help me a lot with the <a href="https://github.com/pranay-gundam/spatial-sims">spatial sims</a> package that has been a work in progress for such a long time. As a recap and update on that, my plans for the package had started almost a year ago around this time but I soon postponed it after realizing how much more I had to learn to get to a position to understand how exactly I could accomplish my goals with the package. I’m not currently at a level of economic maturity where I can just sit down and write all the code myself in a month, but I definitely understand what is going on and I know a lot more than before (understanding <a href="https://github.com/FRBNY-DSGE/DSGE.jl">DSGE.jl</a>, <a href="https://github.com/FRBNY-DSGE/SMC.jl">SMC.jl</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/FRBNY-DSGE/ModelConstructors.jl">ModelConstructors.jl</a> has helped an incredible amount). I’ll still probably need to find people to help me out with it, but the current plan is to get back into writing out the models for the package and coding it up once PhD applications are all submitted (sometime in the beginning of 2025).</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="econ-thoughts"/><category term="tidy-tuesday"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I wanted to start off by saying that Github Co-Pilot is amazing. I’m not super sure about the specifics of what it trains on but it has to somehow look at my git tracked code and give suggestions based on my coding style which is just spectacular. Often times the most demoralizing part of doing a coding project is typing out tedious code that one knows how to write but just takes effort and unnessary mental energy (especially if there are some unintended bugs). Co-Pilot bypasses all of that with just one keystroke; more often than not the code that Co-Pilot writes is not buggy (especially if it’s something not particularly complicated). The greatest thing is that sure you can ask write out a detailed prompt in the chat window for AI to interpret and answer, but Co-Pilot also has an autocomplete feature where you can only write out the name of the function and it does the rest for you (sometimes it even knows what function you want to write next before you type out the name).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">summer of 2024</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/summer-of-2024/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="summer of 2024"/><published>2024-08-10T17:28:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-10T17:28:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/summer-of-2024</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/summer-of-2024/"><![CDATA[<p>The first thing I want to talk about is that I’ve made pretty significant progress on the TidyTuesday front. Turns out that having a very clearly defined project that works with data and nice APIs really gets me motivated to make progress on it. There are always more features and capabilities to add with these sorts of things, but I’m pretty sure I’ll be able to finish the baseline version that works with the Fred API by this weekend and get it up and running to be able to make my first renewed TidyTuesday post by next next Tuesday. Just as a reminder if you didn’t catch the last blog post, the idea is to renew the TidyTuesday series by running a random regression every day and reporting on one of the interesting ones each week; maybe there’s some cool interaction to discover (although very unlikely). I’m also using this as an opportunity to get some practice in writing code to compartmentalize and automatically generate chunks of reports in LaTeX where I only need to contribute to writing some qualitative color and everything else is already taken care of (something that’s a very helpful tool when working with products that are run repetitively with different data or small changes much like the work we do with forecasting on DSGE at the Fed).</p> <p>In other news, this summer is almost to an end. It has gone by both pretty quickly and gruelingly slow at times, but we are now entering quite the stressful era with PhD applications coming up soon. To be honest, I really don’t want to talk much about all the stressful stuff, so here are a few of the new restaurants and bakeries that I’ve been to over the summer that I want to highlight (these are all places in New York):</p> <ul> <li>Dominique Ansel</li> <li>Little Flower Cafe</li> <li>Win Son Bakery (can’t believe it took me this long to go here)</li> <li>NONONO</li> <li>Obica Mozzarella Bar</li> <li>Cafe China</li> <li>Glaze Teriyaki</li> <li>Cha Pa’s Noodles and Grill</li> </ul> <p>I’m not going to talk much about any of these right now, but there is a favorites in NYC so far post that is coming up as well. Along those lines, here are some places that are still on the list and I will be hitting sometime soon:</p> <ul> <li>Lucali’s</li> <li>Steve’s Authentic Key Lime Pie</li> <li>Birdbox (really curious to see if this dethrones Rowdy Rooster as my favorite fried chicken place)</li> </ul> <p>Finally, as a preface for next week, I’ll finally be talking about some of my NSF ideas and a really basic general setup for spatial general equilibrium models that is not necessarily what I’ll be using for NSF but something that may make its way into the eventual spatial-sims package (along with some more ideas about the purpose of the package now that I have a better grasp on the literature).</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal-updates"/><category term="the-pittsburgh-palate"/><category term="tidy-tuesday"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The first thing I want to talk about is that I’ve made pretty significant progress on the TidyTuesday front. Turns out that having a very clearly defined project that works with data and nice APIs really gets me motivated to make progress on it. There are always more features and capabilities to add with these sorts of things, but I’m pretty sure I’ll be able to finish the baseline version that works with the Fred API by this weekend and get it up and running to be able to make my first renewed TidyTuesday post by next next Tuesday. Just as a reminder if you didn’t catch the last blog post, the idea is to renew the TidyTuesday series by running a random regression every day and reporting on one of the interesting ones each week; maybe there’s some cool interaction to discover (although very unlikely). I’m also using this as an opportunity to get some practice in writing code to compartmentalize and automatically generate chunks of reports in LaTeX where I only need to contribute to writing some qualitative color and everything else is already taken care of (something that’s a very helpful tool when working with products that are run repetitively with different data or small changes much like the work we do with forecasting on DSGE at the Fed).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hello on Github! (and refurbishing TidyTuesday)</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/refurbishing-TidyTuesday/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hello on Github! (and refurbishing TidyTuesday)"/><published>2024-08-03T17:45:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-03T17:45:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/refurbishing-TidyTuesday</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/refurbishing-TidyTuesday/"><![CDATA[<p>I have not posted in quite a while and this is mostly because I have been migrating my old website to this new one (which is also thanks to another new friend)! There are still some formatting kinks I want to work out and I need to figure out how to add both a comments section and an email subscriber button, but this will be my website for a long while to come (I am, for the first time, actually quite satisfied with it except for some very minor formatting issues).</p> <p>We will be getting back into our regularly scheduled weekly posts now with a flavor towards stuff I’m learning or experiencing whilst working on NSF just to efficiently multitask (although that being said there are still a lot of post ideas I still have in store as well).</p> <p>One other thing that has been in the back of my mind for a long while is TidyTuesday; I basically only did one post and abandoned it right after that. I realized right after the first post back then that it was not worth the time commitment required to make a quality post week after week. As I’ve been uploading all the blogs back onto the new website and looking at the poor state of TidyTuesday, I remembered a conversation I had with a friend and work team member. We have this running joke about whenever we encounter a roadblock, the solution is to just “run a regression” as the empirical economists do. One day, somehow the conversation diverged to this as well, and we were making jokes about running random regressions one random timeseries. This is what I think I will turn TidyTuesday into: a script that runs automatically every day that picks two random timeseries from the plethora of data APIs and runs a regression between the two. Then every week I pick one of the seven that I found interesting and talk a little bit more about the relationship between the two timeseries.</p> <p>There are of course more details and functionalities I can add into the code to do this (such as picking some controls) but for now the project idea is just to do the automation and generate a systematic report each day (and then automatically push it to github). Regardless, I cannot promise much progress on this for a while between NSF and grad apps but do expect this to show its face by the end of the year.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal-updates"/><category term="tidy-tuesday"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have not posted in quite a while and this is mostly because I have been migrating my old website to this new one (which is also thanks to another new friend)! There are still some formatting kinks I want to work out and I need to figure out how to add both a comments section and an email subscriber button, but this will be my website for a long while to come (I am, for the first time, actually quite satisfied with it except for some very minor formatting issues).]]></summary></entry></feed>