<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-07-30T02:23:55+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Pranay Gundam</title><entry><title type="html">reflections on macro I and monkeying around with OLGs</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/reflections-on-macros/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="reflections on macro I and monkeying around with OLGs"/><published>2024-02-03T13:28:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-03T13:28:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/reflections-on-macros</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/reflections-on-macros/"><![CDATA[<p>(Note: All of the text of this post was written on December 25th, 2023 while the attached pdf has been edited recently)</p> <p>I just finished a Macro Theory I at NYU with Sargent and Ljungqvist. Thankfully I ended up doing well but even more so than that I realized that I have a lot of interest in Macro. Maybe it was the different nature of taking only one class — which allowed me to focus on understanding only one subject thoroughly as opposed to five or six at the same time although I will say that working a job while taking a class is quite difficult — but being immersed in so much econ from class to all the work and seminars at the Fed was a different and enjoyable experience in terms of understanding and getting appreciation of the subject.</p> <p>I found myself naturally thinking about extensions of problems we discussed or how equilibriums would changed if we laxed certain assumptions (“extra thinking” that I would not do if I was in a class at CMU just struggling to keep up with all the course work) and having the time to actually work out examples myself as well. Very refreshing compared to the four year grind. The two topics of discussion that I have become intrigued with and will work on now before I have to focus on grad apps are structural modeling and just working out a few questions I had on OLG models and how they build out to the more involved macro models used on the frontier. I think I would probably be able to answer my questions with a few google searches leading to a handful of papers to read but it feels like a good exercise to put pen to paper and work it out myself.</p> <p>On that end I’ve attached some of the work that I wanted to look into after the class ended on OLGs (and a few of the other blog posts later will be on some of the structural toy models that I want to have in hand going into grad school).</p> <p>In other news, I will be taking Analysis II again at NYU this spring semester (and after that probably won’t take any more classes to focus on apps and other personal projects, although who knows may do Macro II next spring if they offer it) which I have heard is not as bad as analysis at CMU so we shall see how that goes in a few weeks.</p> <iframe src="/assets/pdf/OLG-Monkey.pdf" width="100%" height="1000px"></iframe>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="econ-thoughts"/><category term="personal-updates"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[(All of the text of this post was written on December 25th, 2023 while the attached pdf has been edited recently)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is all this?</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2023/What-is-all-this/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is all this?"/><published>2023-06-11T19:49:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-11T19:49:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2023/What-is-all-this</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2023/What-is-all-this/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve always heard about habit enforcement mechanisms: people posting videos of their workouts on social media, money bets that would make an individual lose money if they regressed to their bad habits, or even simple self rewards if an individual met a certain habit goal of theirs. I’ve never, however, really invested any time or effort into these so called “habit enforcement mechanisms” myself. There have been a lot of habits that I’ve genuinely wanted to adopt since basically middle school. A few of them have actually stuck but the fast majority have fallen to the wayside, so here I am trying something new. It’s interesting because I’ve always thought about writing a blog but I shudder at the thought of making my personal life public: posting something on the internet feels like a big commitment and this is more so the case when it is regarding issues related to who I am as a person. When you talk to a person face-to-face you get instant feedback about what it is you are saying and you are only talking to one person at one moment in time; things on the internet can reach any stranger at whatever moment in time. I don’t know if I’ve really related my thoughts in the right manner so far (I feel like when I write, it is in general a very disorganized stream of consciousness type of style) but tldr: I find posting things on the internet quite scary. This is especially the case after seeing a lot of well put together blogs written by people I really respect: classmates from high school and college, random people I’ve found on the internet, and others who are in places in their lives that I also want to be in.</p> <p>As such, the main purpose of this blog is not really some place to air out my intimate thoughts on stuff going on in my life (there might be a few scattered posts here and there, who really knows), but rather a sort of tracker of stuff I find interesting and talk about things I’ve learned that excite me.</p> <p>I’m about to head to NYC to start a two year long experience (as a research analyst on the DSGE team at the Federal Reserve) where I intend on learning as much as I can before applying to grad school. This blog is meant to keep track of my progress over at least these two coming years.</p> <p>P.S: Please do not roast me on anything related to grammar. I am sure there will be a lot of mistakes.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal-updates"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve always heard about habit enforcement mechanisms: people posting videos of their workouts on social media, money bets that would make an individual lose money if they regressed to their bad habits, or even simple self rewards if an individual met a certain habit goal of theirs. I’ve never, however, really invested any time or effort into these so called “habit enforcement mechanisms” myself. There have been a lot of habits that I’ve genuinely wanted to adopt since basically middle school. A few of them have actually stuck but the fast majority have fallen to the wayside, so here I am trying something new. It’s interesting because I’ve always thought about writing a blog but I shudder at the thought of making my personal life public: posting something on the internet feels like a big commitment and this is more so the case when it is regarding issues related to who I am as a person. When you talk to a person face-to-face you get instant feedback about what it is you are saying and you are only talking to one person at one moment in time; things on the internet can reach any stranger at whatever moment in time. I don’t know if I’ve really related my thoughts in the right manner so far (I feel like when I write, it is in general a very disorganized stream of consciousness type of style) but tldr: I find posting things on the internet quite scary. This is especially the case after seeing a lot of well put together blogs written by people I really respect: classmates from high school and college, random people I’ve found on the internet, and others who are in places in their lives that I also want to be in.]]></summary></entry></feed>