<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-07-31T01:30:33+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Pranay Gundam</title><entry><title type="html">the game theory of mutually assured destruction</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/the-game-theory-of-mutually-assured-destruction/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the game theory of mutually assured destruction"/><published>2024-06-23T21:36:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-23T21:36:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/the-game-theory-of-mutually-assured-destruction</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/the-game-theory-of-mutually-assured-destruction/"><![CDATA[<p>I have been getting a lot of ideas/questions from the Remembrance of Earth’s Past series. One of the concepts that shows up towards the end of the second book, The Dark Forest, and is discussed in a lot more detail in the third book, Death’s End, is the deterrence through mutually assured destruction or MAD.</p> <p>One quick tangent: I searched up what exactly the definition of MAD entails and although the definition of the terminology itself should apply, the term itself in the context of what it was made for applies specifically to mutually assured destruction through nuclear weapons with a first strike against a nation with second strike capabilities. So I’m not super sure if MAD the best term to describe what was happening in Death’s End since it was only one side threatening the destruction of both parties, in the book they call it simply “Dark Forest Deterrence” but for the sake of this post I’ll continue to call it MAD just because it does have logical parallels to the origin of the term (and also MAD is fewer characters to type out each time)</p> <p>In the book, the way MAD was threatened was through an “universal broadcast” that Earth could send out that included the located of the alien species’ star system and since humankind’s system and Trisolaris’ system were so close together that this would cause other alien species to discover the solar system as well. The reason why discovery was so scary was because this series ascribes to the “Dark Forest” explanation as to why alien civilizations were so hard to find: that all the surviving civilizations were very technologically advanced groups who distrusted every other civilization by default and operated under a “shoot on sight” protocol so broadcasting one’s location would get them immediately annihilated. In the case of Earth, this broadcast system was under control of a single individual. This, of course, was an immense responsibility since they were in control of the fate of two civilizations. So, in picking who that individual would be, one would have to make sure that it would be a person who would not activate the signal needlessly, but also give the impression that they would activate the signal when being attacked.</p> <p>This is a very similar issue to what the US had faced during the Cold War. Whenever I watch documentaries or listen to podcasts on the subject, they always talk about how there was so much research being done on this MAD-related game theory problem. For most of my life prior, I always thought that this was really silly given that my impression was that game theory was one of those simple 2x2 games. In retrospect now, I realize that to truly model the complexity of what is going on and include more nuances specific to the situation, you have to consider the exact mechanisms by which a MAD situation would be activated. Questions such as: who exactly has control of the launch, are they likely to retaliate even if they already know they are doomed, are there multiple people involved in the launching of nuclear weapons, how do you maximize the perception of one’s threat against their opponent without sacrificing other things? All these are questions that can be incorporated into a model that make the question a bit more interesting than one of those “2x2 Find the Nash Equilibria” games.</p> <p>I’ll detail one such model soon, but just for some context we can make to the archetypical 2x2 we see in high school Econ classes (note: that most of these changes are taken as part of a standard model in game theory in the literature, I’m not too read up on it so I may be missing a few key components):</p> <ul> <li>Tack on some functional structure for the probabilities that both the first and second strike of MAD are activated.</li> <li>Introduce multiple actions (with complete destruction being minus infinity utility). One can even make it an action that lies on some continuous domain instead of discrete choices.</li> <li>For games with sequential actions, we can represent the problem as nested games with each action taken further filtering the state spacetakes.</li> </ul> <p>With all that in mind, let’s try to construct a model for a Cold War-type situation between two world powers.</p> <iframe src="/assets/pdf/modeling-MAD.pdf" width="100%" height="1000px"></iframe>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="econ-thoughts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Note, Some spoilers for the Remembrance of Earth's Past series]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">reflections on macro I and monkeying around with OLGs</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/first-food-post-pt2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="reflections on macro I and monkeying around with OLGs"/><published>2024-06-11T19:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-11T19:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/first-food-post-pt2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/first-food-post-pt2/"><![CDATA[<p>I’m still cooking up another game theory-related post that will take a bit more time to finish (and so here is another Pittsburgh-related food post). The last post covered only some of the neighborhoods in Pittsburgh, so here is the other batch of places the typical CMU student only goes to sometimes.</p> <ul> <li>Strip District: This neighborhood is well-known for the food scene and the grocery stores. When I lived in North Oakland I would occasionally walk here (which, in retrospect, was a very sketchy path). I used to go to the Strip District a bit during freshman year since this is where the Red Cross office is in Pittsburgh. <ul> <li>Restaurant: Coop de Ville (although I have not bought food from this place in person) is my absolute favorite takeout fried chicken place. I’ve gotten GrubHub delivery from there many times.</li> <li>Coffee: De Fer Coffee and Tea happens to be my favorite coffee shop to work at in Pittsburgh just because of the vibe and the ability to take a nice walk in a cool area afterward.</li> <li>Misc: Klavons, which unfortunately may not be open anymore, is my favorite ice cream parlor in Pittsburgh. I happen to be a fan of sundaes and Klavons is miles above the competition. Also, Macaroni Company is a cool grocery store.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Downtown: I rarely went downtown sophomore and junior years (because of the pandemic) and so I didn’t have as much exposure to this area of Pittsburgh as I did many of the others. The one factor that did help me get more familiar with the area was that I interned at PNC the summer before my senior year which, in addition to being able to go out for lunch, introduced me to a lot of people who also had their lists of Pittsburgh favorites. <ul> <li>Coffee: I never managed to go to Gasoline Street Coffee Company until after I had graduated but it has a nice vibe (they have a chess board) and has pretty good coffee.</li> <li>Lunch Places: Arrepittas has a filling combo platter that would always satisfy my craving for Latin American food. Sree’s Foods on the other hand was one of the few Indian places I enjoyed in Pittsburgh. It was started by this couple from Hyderabad and I feel like they would give me a little extra food when I spoke in Telugu.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Lawrenceville: This is a neighborhood that is known for some refined restaurants. I’ve only been here a few times so I can’t speak to much. <ul> <li>Restaurant: Picolo forno is a nice Italian place; can’t say much more than I enjoyed my experience there. Condado’s on the other hand is a Pittsburgh classic (known for its fusion tacos) and whenever I get takeout from Condados’s it’s always from this specific location.</li> <li>Coffee: I have surprisingly been to a handful of coffee shops here but Espresso a Mano stands above the rest.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Southside: Although there are a few spots that I absolutely adore from this neighborhood I’ve actually only visited in person two-three times. <ul> <li>Restaurant: The place I’ve gotten the most takeout from in Pittsburgh is Cilantro and Ajo (I don’t even remember how many times now). The plantains side dish is by far the best plantains I have ever eaten and their cilantro crema is also absolutely amazing.</li> <li>Coffee: Delanie’s Coffee is my pick for the Southside. Not going to lie this is the only coffee place I have gotten coffee from in Southside but it was still pretty decent.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Northside: Most people don’t even know the name of this neighborhood other than the fact that it’s home to The Mattress Factory. I can’t say I’m much better to be honest though since this is the neighborhood that I’ve been to the least (although I did know the name). <ul> <li>Restaurant/Coffee: 40 North at Alphabet City is the only place I’ve been that I feel is worth putting on this list. There’s an attached bookshop, and bookshop food combined places are always pretty cool.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Bloomfield: This neighborhood in my opinion is a weird in between going places neighborhood and so I’ve grouped an interesting swath of area into this place. <ul> <li>Restaurant: The first time I went to Apteka I had an amazing time. The second time I will say was not nearly as good of a time as the first and so I’m conflicted since I came out of the place the first time thinking that it was the best restaurant in Pittsburgh and the second time thinking it was subpar. Regardless it’s a place that has to be mentioned.</li> <li>Coffee: Ineffable Ca Phe is a Vietnamese place that, in addition to coffee, also sells Bahn Mi’s. It also has a lot of space and quite a few outlets so nice place to camp out to get some work done.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Other mentions: Wheelfish is the best barbeque place I have been to in Pittsburgh (although it is in some suburban neighborhood that requires a car to get to). The Exchange is actually on the CMU campus and one of the places I think 90% of CMU students can agree upon as being good.</li> </ul> <p>So that’s my big list of places I wanted to write down somewhere and share. I will also reiterate my list is from the perspective of a college student who is on a budget 99% of the time. I know for a fact that there are some places (especially Downtown, West Southside, and the Strip District) where some better-endowed people tend to go. Regardless I’m confident that anyone will have a good time at each of the places on my list.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="the-pittsburgh-palate"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’m still cooking up another game theory-related post that will take a bit more time to finish (and so here is another Pittsburgh-related food post). The last post covered only some of the neighborhoods in Pittsburgh, so here is the other batch of places the typical CMU student only goes to sometimes.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Key &amp;amp; Peele teacher draft in real life and the benefits of socio-political gridlock</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/KeyPeele-teacher-draft/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Key &amp;amp; Peele teacher draft in real life and the benefits of socio-political gridlock"/><published>2024-05-25T11:28:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-25T11:28:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/KeyPeele-teacher-draft</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/KeyPeele-teacher-draft/"><![CDATA[<p>Back in high school, I watched a lot of Key and Peele. One of my favorite skits was “If We Treated Teachers Like Pro Athletes” (the video below).</p> <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/aYOg8EON29Y" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe> <p>Even though this is a joke, this seems to me like a low-key intriguing idea that seems unexplored. In theory, since public schools are all government-controlled, we already have a big central organization that regulates the hiring and rules of the “league” (public elementary and secondary education).</p> <p>The hiring process for teachers in public schools is similar to that of most industries; applicants search for their positions and submit applications for those spots. Drafts on the other hand are incredibly different. The choice is taken out of the hands of the applicant (the teachers in this case or the players in the case of sports drafts) for the most part - other than simply refusing to cooperate or expressing interest in a specific hirer beforehand - and the decision making is put into the hands of the hirers. Schools still have the choice in the current system to hire who they want, but they cannot control who applies for the positions that need filling. A draft system would enable schools to target specific individuals in particular growth areas. As a summary, the effects of implementing a draft would be</p> <ul> <li>More equity across schools in teaching quality</li> <li>Ability to enhance particular areas in need of improvement with targeted bids</li> <li>Shift of social/cultural perception of teachers</li> </ul> <p>There is no free lunch, and I also thought of a couple of costs to this draft model:</p> <ul> <li>Good teachers can only do so much to help the quality of underfunded schools</li> <li>Teachers do not get as much agency to act according to their preferences</li> <li>More money is required to compensate teachers appropriately</li> </ul> <p>I wanted to be a bit more quantitative and build out some sort of comparative model where I look at equilibrium in a free hiring model and equilibrium under a draft market model of how much it would cost schools, but to be honest, I simply don’t have the time or mental capacity for that this weekend.</p> <p>All this speaks to a larger movement to fix the education system that calls for putting more social value in the teaching profession to attract more good teachers. Fixes related to calls for systemic changes in societal values, though easy in practice, are quite difficult to bring about. Each of the social niches is so entrenched in its own culture that a large, all-encompassing social movement is hard to come by and requires a monumental force of social engineering that causes such as fixing the education system - although quite agreed upon that it is an issue - currently don’t have the right powerful people backing it to bring about concrete change.</p> <p>Speaking of powerful people and politics, I wanted to take a right turn and talk about something that occurred to me while reading Ken Liu’s The Perfect Match (the more of his short stories I read, the more I realized shows like Black Mirror and Love, Death, and Robots take inspiration from and even use in the case of Good Hunting).</p> <p>It is quite difficult to watch the news or even just live your normal life in the US and not become frustrated with the fact that the sociopolitical views of various groups in the US are so antagonistically polarized. It’s an emotion that I periodically feel and a sentiment echoed across many of my peers. Recently, however, after reading Ken Liu’s The Perfect Match, I’ve thought about the issue differently.</p> <p>To summarize the book, it’s a typical dystopian story of a company that grows so large that they imbue themselves into every part of your life and monitor you so much that they have stored a data version of yourself. Even though I’ve consumed a lot of media like this, this time I was especially reflective about the reality of this situation.</p> <p>Would something that crazy ever be able to happen in real life? Sure, there are small signs of privacy concerns amongst all the tech giants, but for some reason, I just had this underlying belief that something like that would not happen in real life.</p> <p>I think of the public hearings against Zuckerberg and TikTok’s CEO Shou Zi Chew. It was clear how distrustful some politicians were about technology and how many others echoed the same concern.</p> <p>It hit me then that for a company to grow that out of control feels like it requires uniform support of it, and the socio-political divide of today makes it such that even if one side were to provide staunch support, the other side would be in staunch opposition. Even on both sides, we have so much entertainment showing how things can spiral out of control that I can now sit here typing this out without much worry that these scenarios will come to be.</p> <p>I’ve always abstractly understood the need for diversity of thoughts and opinions, but I’ve always felt like this leads to gridlock and halts progress. It’s only now that I’m able to appreciate a concrete example of a substantial positive reason for moving slowly amongst all the cons.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="econ-thoughts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Back in high school, I watched a lot of Key and Peele. One of my favorite skits was “If We Treated Teachers Like Pro Athletes” (the video below).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">reflections on macro I and monkeying around with OLGs</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/reflections-on-macros/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="reflections on macro I and monkeying around with OLGs"/><published>2024-02-03T13:28:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-03T13:28:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/reflections-on-macros</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/reflections-on-macros/"><![CDATA[<p>(Note: All of the text of this post was written on December 25th, 2023 while the attached pdf has been edited recently)</p> <p>I just finished a Macro Theory I at NYU with Sargent and Ljungqvist. Thankfully I ended up doing well but even more so than that I realized that I have a lot of interest in Macro. Maybe it was the different nature of taking only one class — which allowed me to focus on understanding only one subject thoroughly as opposed to five or six at the same time although I will say that working a job while taking a class is quite difficult — but being immersed in so much econ from class to all the work and seminars at the Fed was a different and enjoyable experience in terms of understanding and getting appreciation of the subject.</p> <p>I found myself naturally thinking about extensions of problems we discussed or how equilibriums would changed if we laxed certain assumptions (“extra thinking” that I would not do if I was in a class at CMU just struggling to keep up with all the course work) and having the time to actually work out examples myself as well. Very refreshing compared to the four year grind. The two topics of discussion that I have become intrigued with and will work on now before I have to focus on grad apps are structural modeling and just working out a few questions I had on OLG models and how they build out to the more involved macro models used on the frontier. I think I would probably be able to answer my questions with a few google searches leading to a handful of papers to read but it feels like a good exercise to put pen to paper and work it out myself.</p> <p>On that end I’ve attached some of the work that I wanted to look into after the class ended on OLGs (and a few of the other blog posts later will be on some of the structural toy models that I want to have in hand going into grad school).</p> <p>In other news, I will be taking Analysis II again at NYU this spring semester (and after that probably won’t take any more classes to focus on apps and other personal projects, although who knows may do Macro II next spring if they offer it) which I have heard is not as bad as analysis at CMU so we shall see how that goes in a few weeks.</p> <iframe src="/assets/pdf/OLG-Monkey.pdf" width="100%" height="1000px"></iframe>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="econ-thoughts"/><category term="personal-updates"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[(All of the text of this post was written on December 25th, 2023 while the attached pdf has been edited recently)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">what is all this?</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2023/What-is-all-this/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="what is all this?"/><published>2023-06-11T19:49:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-11T19:49:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2023/What-is-all-this</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2023/What-is-all-this/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve always heard about habit enforcement mechanisms: people posting videos of their workouts on social media, money bets that would make an individual lose money if they regressed to their bad habits, or even simple self-rewards if an individual met a certain habit goal of theirs. I’ve never, however, really invested any time or effort into these so-called “habit enforcement mechanisms” myself. There have been a lot of habits that I’ve genuinely wanted to adopt since basically middle school. A few of them have actually stuck but the vast majority have fallen to the wayside; so here I am trying something new. It’s interesting because I’ve always thought about writing a blog but I shudder at the thought of making my personal life public: posting something on the internet feels like a big commitment and this is more so the case when it is regarding issues related to who I am as a person. When you talk to a person face-to-face you get instant feedback about what it is you are saying and you are only talking to one person at one moment in time; things on the internet can reach any stranger at whatever moment in time. I don’t know if I’ve really related my thoughts in the right manner so far (I feel like when I write, it is in general a very disorganized stream of consciousness type of style) but TL;DR: I find posting things on the internet quite scary. This is especially the case after seeing a lot of well put together blogs written by people I really respect: classmates from high school and college, random people I’ve found on the internet, and others who are in places in their lives that I also want to be in.</p> <p>As such, the main purpose of this blog is not really some place to air out my intimate thoughts on things going on in my life (there might be a few scattered posts here and there, who really knows), but rather a sort of tracker of things I find interesting and discuss what I’ve learned that excites me.</p> <p>I’m about to head to NYC to start a two-year-long experience (as a research analyst on the DSGE team at the Federal Reserve) where I intend on learning as much as I can before applying to grad school. This blog is meant to keep track of my progress over at least these two coming years.</p> <p>P.S: Please do not roast me on anything related to grammar. I am sure there will be a lot of mistakes.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal-updates"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve always heard about habit enforcement mechanisms: people posting videos of their workouts on social media, money bets that would make an individual lose money if they regressed to their bad habits, or even simple self-rewards if an individual met a certain habit goal of theirs. I’ve never, however, really invested any time or effort into these so-called “habit enforcement mechanisms” myself. There have been a lot of habits that I’ve genuinely wanted to adopt since basically middle school. A few of them have actually stuck but the vast majority have fallen to the wayside; so here I am trying something new. It’s interesting because I’ve always thought about writing a blog but I shudder at the thought of making my personal life public: posting something on the internet feels like a big commitment and this is more so the case when it is regarding issues related to who I am as a person. When you talk to a person face-to-face you get instant feedback about what it is you are saying and you are only talking to one person at one moment in time; things on the internet can reach any stranger at whatever moment in time. I don’t know if I’ve really related my thoughts in the right manner so far (I feel like when I write, it is in general a very disorganized stream of consciousness type of style) but TL;DR: I find posting things on the internet quite scary. This is especially the case after seeing a lot of well put together blogs written by people I really respect: classmates from high school and college, random people I’ve found on the internet, and others who are in places in their lives that I also want to be in.]]></summary></entry></feed>