<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-09-07T13:04:57+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Pranay Gundam</title><entry><title type="html">things i find boring</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/boredom/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="things i find boring"/><published>2024-09-06T22:50:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-06T22:50:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/boredom</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/boredom/"><![CDATA[<p>My headphones are in a really dire situation. They’re wireless and so when I lost one of the pairs a few months ago I tried to manage with just the right piece. I’m constantly scared that taking the subway everyday, with its loud noises, is going to render me deaf eventually, so I really value the noise canceling; riding the subway with just the right headphone was a game of angling the right side of my head towards the sounds. Since then, the situation has deteriorated further and my remaining headphone piece is now broken, which makes my subway daily commutes completely headphoneless. This is quite boring, to say the least. No more podcasts, no more music, no more isolating myself in a bubble of noise canceling. I’m usually an avid people watcher — at least in public situations where that’s not awkward — but that’s not something you can do on a subway. If you happen to make awkward eye contact with someone its not like you just walk past each other, you’re going to have to sit right across from them for a decent while.</p> <p>I feel like my writing is pretty boring. Rather, to be specific, my writing is boring to those who don’t get excited by the same sorts of econ questions or coding projects as I do which I’ve discovered — now that I have left CMU — is a far smaller population than I previously thought. I’ve done this blog more so for myself, and as an outlet to put some of the econ thoughts in my head on paper so I don’t particularly care if what I write is the most engaging thing on the planet or not but the other day but the other day a friend (and fellow blog reader), showed me another <a href="https://splishsplash.online/p/towards-understanding">blog post</a> that captured me so much even though it had nothing to do with anything that I’m usually interested with. I’ve also been reading a handful of other economists’ blogs and I’ve come to the conclusion that even beyond being a good, economist I want to also be a good communicator. So now I am inspired to focus on not only what I am saying but also how I am saying it.</p> <p>That being said, there is no way I could close off a post without talking about something econ-related. Something that is so pervasive of an issue in macro economics is solving macro models where the state space (the matrix of basic information about the world that the model has to keep track of) is large. In short, it’s quite difficult to build interestingly nuanced models because we are always limited by this fact. I personally find this to be such a boring issue; it’s not an issue of writing a better defined model or one of finding some new mechanism but just that there are too many things to keep track of. The research into finding ways to solve these large dimensional state space systems does seem interesting but the problem itself seems so blunt and dull.</p> <p>Regardless, I actually strongly believe that regularly being bored for bouts of time throughout the week really draws out one’s creativity. I’m not anti-technology, but I do believe that the creative part of people’s minds is something that is less exercised nowadays given the trend of constant stimulus and content aimed at short attention spans. That being said, I don’t think that sitting in one place and mindlessly staring into the sky is exercising this creative muscle (there is a different time and place for meditative practice), but to properly exercise, one has to actively put themselves in a scenario with little stimulus and start imagining what they want. The reason why I started this blog was because I wanted a place to formalize all those random subway thoughts that come to mind when I’m sitting there bored out of my mind. One distinction that I did want to make before I close is the difference between being bored and doing something that is boring. Although doing something boring may indeed be important, I don’t think this is actively beneficial for flexing those creativity muscles.</p> <p><em>This post was a little bit different from the others I’ve done so far just thematically. I’ve never thought of myself as a writer per se and still don’t, but I think it is a skill that I want to actively work on going into the future, so you may see many different types of posts to come.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal-updates"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My headphones are in a really dire situation. They’re wireless and so when I lost one of the pairs a few months ago I tried to manage with just the right piece. I’m constantly scared that taking the subway everyday, with its loud noises, is going to render me deaf eventually, so I really value the noise canceling; riding the subway with just the right headphone was a game of angling the right side of my head towards the sounds. Since then, the situation has deteriorated further and my remaining headphone piece is now broken, which makes my subway daily commutes completely headphoneless. This is quite boring, to say the least. No more podcasts, no more music, no more isolating myself in a bubble of noise canceling. I’m usually an avid people watcher — at least in public situations where that’s not awkward — but that’s not something you can do on a subway. If you happen to make awkward eye contact with someone its not like you just walk past each other, you’re going to have to sit right across from them for a decent while.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">labor day weekend</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/labor-day-weekend/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="labor day weekend"/><published>2024-08-31T19:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-31T19:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/labor-day-weekend</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/labor-day-weekend/"><![CDATA[<p>The pressure from all the upcoming deadlines is really rearing its head now. I personally find it best to just set my mind to focus on one thing at a time; for example, during college, I could just set out an order in which to do all the problem sets I had and just focus solely on each one until they were done. However, I think that strategy does not bode well in a situation where I have to do my normal Fed work, NSF, GRE, etc. It’s not the worst; it’s just that I have to get really good at shifting modalities, but I’ve been slowly getting better at it.</p> <p>I did promise a follow-up post to last week’s discussion of modeling politician decision-making, and that is still being worked on, but I have a few other things I need to focus on, so that will have to be postponed for a later week. I did want to say, though, that there are quite a few addenda that need to be added to make sure I’m being satisfactorily accurate and descriptive.</p> <p>In other news, this long weekend is quite well needed. I’ve been told that I usually say that even if I don’t do much each weekend, I actually do get around, and I’ll finally be going to a play (Harry Potter and the Cursed Child). This week I also finally managed to go to <a href="https://birdbox.nyc/">Birdbox</a>, and it is indeed quite good. It does not, however, take the spot as my favorite fried chicken sandwich. It is definitely number two, but the flavors in a Rowdy Rooster sandwich just hit differently (it’s probably the Indian in me).</p> <p>Short post this week since I’m grinding NSF and GRE prep. Until next week!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal-updates"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The pressure from all the upcoming deadlines is really rearing its head now. I personally find it best to just set my mind to focus on one thing at a time; for example, during college, I could just set out an order in which to do all the problem sets I had and just focus solely on each one until they were done. However, I think that strategy does not bode well in a situation where I have to do my normal Fed work, NSF, GRE, etc. It’s not the worst; it’s just that I have to get really good at shifting modalities, but I’ve been slowly getting better at it.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the dynamics of incumbent politicians pt. 1</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/dynamics-of-politicians/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the dynamics of incumbent politicians pt. 1"/><published>2024-08-26T22:05:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-26T22:05:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/dynamics-of-politicians</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/dynamics-of-politicians/"><![CDATA[<p>I went to a Stephen Colbert show recently (you can actually see me in a few of the audience shots), and all things considered, it was quite an interesting experience. Everything is very streamlined (it makes sense given that they have a lot of practice with it), down to even the bathroom breaks. They do a lot of encouraging the audience to have big reactions to jokes or guests coming on stage, which is something that I expected, but being in the audience live gives you a different sense of responsibility for enriching the experience of the TV audience.</p> <p>Otherwise, it was a lot more political than I remember it being, which in retrospect does make sense given the upcoming presidential election. I don’t remember being this inundated with political content last election cycle, despite living in a more swing state than NY, but I’m seeing political content everywhere now, especially on YouTube.</p> <p>As an aside, I was rewatching Oppenheimer a couple of weeks ago (which, as another aside, has taken the place of my favorite movie of all time, a spot I could not definitively fill until Oppenheimer. I am truly so sad that I could not watch it in theaters) and realized how different the politicians seemed in that age compared to my perception of politicians now (on either side of the aisle, to be honest). They just seemed so much smarter and more calculated rather than just spouting random brazen comments all willy-nilly. I feel the term “career politician” has been cast aside as an undesired trait in the past few election cycles, but I think that there may be a shift back towards “the swamp” in the sense of the intelligence and an all-around put-togetherness of our candidates. Right now, Pete Buttigieg strikes me as the most put-together politician who does think deeply about policy issues and is able to convey the depth of his thought publicly as well, but maybe there are a lot of people like this that I don’t know about because I’m not that much into politics. I don’t know too much about John McCain, but I’ve been seeing quite a few videos about him on my YouTube feed recently, and it reminded me of a different class of politicians who held high certain virtues which distance them from the current “Trumpism” effect.</p> <p>Amidst that, it’s interesting to see how old Republican politicians who have acted in very different ways have turned to embrace the new Trump-era tactics and think about the incentive structure that leads them to so rapidly adopt the new regime.</p> <p>All this has brought me back to this day last year when I was thinking generally about politics and what the incentives that dictate the way politicians act as they do are. Back then, I never really arrived at something that motivated me to make a full-fledged post. I’ve now since revisited the question, and it took me a little bit, but I think I’ve been able to put something together to model the behavior of politicians in a neat way. So with that said, before I close off for you to get into the PDF (although I’m in Markdown now with the new website, doing the LaTeX separately for the most part is still much better), this topic will be a two-post series. Today I first talk about the model in depth, and next week I’ll try to get my in-page Jupyter notebook feature working for you all to see some code to make some pretty visuals and see how one would address this question empirically.</p> <iframe src="/assets/pdf/incumbent-politicians.pdf" width="100%" height="1000px"></iframe>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="econ-thoughts"/><category term="personal-updates"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I went to a Stephen Colbert show recently (you can actually see me in a few of the audience shots), and all things considered, it was quite an interesting experience. Everything is very streamlined (it makes sense given that they have a lot of practice with it), down to even the bathroom breaks. They do a lot of encouraging the audience to have big reactions to jokes or guests coming on stage, which is something that I expected, but being in the audience live gives you a different sense of responsibility for enriching the experience of the TV audience.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Brief TidyTuesday Update</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/TTupdate/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Brief TidyTuesday Update"/><published>2024-08-20T07:38:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-20T07:38:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/TTupdate</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/TTupdate/"><![CDATA[<p>There was supposed to be a post up today and I do indeed have all the materials prepped for this, but I am still trying to mess around with the latex report generation and the best way to format everything so I’m gonna have to wait till next week to do the first post of the refurbished series.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="tidy-tuesday"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There was supposed to be a post up today and I do indeed have all the materials prepped for this, but I am still trying to mess around with the latex report generation and the best way to format everything so I’m gonna have to wait till next week to do the first post of the refurbished series.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">spatial models update and stanning for github copilot</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/github-copilot-fan-post/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="spatial models update and stanning for github copilot"/><published>2024-08-17T19:10:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-17T19:10:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/github-copilot-fan-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/github-copilot-fan-post/"><![CDATA[<p>I wanted to start off by saying that Github Co-Pilot is amazing. I’m not super sure about the specifics of what it trains on but it has to somehow look at my git tracked code and give suggestions based on my coding style which is just spectacular. Often times the most demoralizing part of doing a coding project is typing out tedious code that one knows how to write but just takes effort and unnessary mental energy (especially if there are some unintended bugs). Co-Pilot bypasses all of that with just one keystroke; more often than not the code that Co-Pilot writes is not buggy (especially if it’s something not particularly complicated). The greatest thing is that sure you can ask write out a detailed prompt in the chat window for AI to interpret and answer, but Co-Pilot also has an autocomplete feature where you can only write out the name of the function and it does the rest for you (sometimes it even knows what function you want to write next before you type out the name).</p> <p>Then also, before I get into the spatial stuff, one update on <a href="https://github.com/pranay-gundam/TidyTuesday">TidyTuesday</a>. The code is still a work in progress; I still need to get it to a state where I’m satisfied enough to not touch it for a while. That being said, it is currently functional. Meaning I can go on with my TidyTuesday blog series plans but there’s still a little to be done to make it fully automated and also include data from more than just Fred.</p> <p>With those two things out of the way, I want to talk a little about spatial econ. I’m not really sure what it is about spatial models that really captures me. If I were to guess, I know I have had somewhat of an interest in the movement of peoples and how they organize in the context of a city for a while since highschool and it was this interest that leaned me towards doing something spatial related for my senior thesis which has then kept me interested in the field.</p> <p>Before I learned a lot of macro, however, I used to think that there was something intrinsically different between the model written in the spatial literature and those in the general macro setting. This may be just from ignorance of not knowing the general questions that a macro model uses to motivate itself, but in my involvement in the spatial literature thus far I have realized that the inherent motivation is very similar: households making a selection from some choice set to maximize their utility given some budget constraints that introduce unique mechanics. There are few key components of a spatial general equilibrium models that I’ve found are the key marked differences between the two:</p> <ul> <li>The choice set for households (also firms as well for models that include those) is expanded to choosing places to live (and work). Models can differ vastly in terms of when these choices are made or restrictions on how such a choice is made but the commuting costs of households and goods is what gives birth to the rich spatial dynamics that relate the model to reality.</li> <li>Location (blocks) have unique characteristics (which can be anything from natural landmarks to the vibes of a neighborhood) that are incorporated into the model in various ways <ul> <li>Household preferences for these characteristics</li> <li>local productivity shocks and spillover effects</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>These two differences are what drive the unique analysis that we can do with spatial models. For example, we can look at how the migration flows (either people moving their residence or working location) change in response to a local productivity shock, or we can see the extent of the effect that local spillovers have on the composition of households in a location. This may seem a bit abstract to those non-macroeconomics readers in terms of the mechanics of the math, so let’s dive into some more specifics.</p> <p>At its core, a structural macro model is built on connecting the optimization problems of various groups of different types of agents. For the toy model we are building now:</p> <ul> <li>There is a discount factor \(\beta \in (0,1)\) and capital depreciation rate \(\delta \in [0,1]\).</li> <li>Let there be \(N\) many location blocks in which households choose to live and work. Each location also has a living amenity rate \(A_i\) which factors into a household’s utility function.</li> <li>A household is an agent who lives forever and faces the main problem of choosing how much of a good to consume at each point in time \(c_t\), how much time to spend on leisure \(l_t\) instead of working, and which location blocks \(i\) and \(j\) to live and work in respectively (they have to pay a commuting fee \(d_{i,j}\) for every time period based on the chosen \(i\) and \(j\)). Households also have the ability to save from time period to time period and these savings affect (this very nebulous and confusing concept to those not in econ that we call) capital \(k_t\).</li> <li>There are no firms in this world; rather, households “make money” using a production function \(Z_{i_t}\cdot F(k_t, 1 - l_t)\) which uses some function \(F\) to relate how much a household produces based on how much capital they possess and how much time they spend working instead of as leisure time. The \(Z_{i_t}\) is a location-specific random process that all have different means and variances that the households are not sure about, so that one’s working location has an effect on how much they are able to produce: since the process is different for each location, each location has different shocks as well. <ul> <li>This is where I’m making the spatial model “interesting”. The model isn’t just incorporating the spatial component by making households choose where they want to live and work based on which is the best place to live in terms of the amenities and distance to work but also which has good future prospects for location productivity.</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>Specifically, the households solve the following optimization problem \(\max_{c_t, l_t, i_t, j_t} \sum_{t=0}^\infty \beta^t u(c_t, l_t, A_{i_t})\) subject to constraints \(c_t + d_{i_t, j_t} + s_t \leq Z_{i_t}\cdot F(k_t, 1 - l_t)\) to dictate the production/saving and \(k_{t+1} = \delta k_t + s_t\) to dictate the capital.</p> <p>It took me a bit of training to be able to do this, but from the problem statement above you can already paint a qualitative picture of the push and pull that affects the households. They want to choose a location to live in with high location amenities, but they also want it to be close to their work, and they also want to choose a place to work that they think has good prospects for its productivity that factors into the households’ production function (their way of making money). They can also turn the levers of how they make money by saving money for the future to build up their capital. There’s a lot going on already without adding too much complexity; don’t get me started on how to solve and estimate these models.</p> <p>There are plenty more features we can build into this to make it more interesting or realistic, such as introducing firms, government agents, or some intrinsic heterogeneity between households; for example, some households can have low levels of education while others can have higher, which affects their respective production functions and may influence their migratory decisions. My NSF proposal will likely tinker with a couple of these “bonus” features and study them in the context of government policy and their spatial implications.</p> <p>Of course, not even I would say that the model we built above is consistent with reality, and even if we were to relax a few assumptions, we would still be nowhere close. This brings me to a point of economic maturity that I’ve come to learn over the past year. Very rarely in econ are people who are doing these structural models caught up with trying to replicate reality; it is more about exploring the relative effects of some channels on others that is what is interesting in monetary policy research. As always, my blog posts are very stream-of-consciousness and more so a personal outlet for me to espouse some thoughts, so I’m not sure how coherent any of the above is to an outside reader. If you want to know more or are confused (most people reading probably know me in real life, so texting is also good 😊).</p> <p>So to close off, the NSF application is coming along and will help me a lot with the <a href="https://github.com/pranay-gundam/spatial-sims">spatial sims</a> package that has been a work in progress for such a long time. As a recap and update on that, my plans for the package had started almost a year ago around this time but I soon postponed it after realizing how much more I had to learn to get to a position to understand how exactly I could accomplish my goals with the package. I’m not currently at a level of economic maturity where I can just sit down and write all the code myself in a month, but I definitely understand what is going on and I know a lot more than before (understanding <a href="https://github.com/FRBNY-DSGE/DSGE.jl">DSGE.jl</a>, <a href="https://github.com/FRBNY-DSGE/SMC.jl">SMC.jl</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/FRBNY-DSGE/ModelConstructors.jl">ModelConstructors.jl</a> has helped an incredible amount). I’ll still probably need to find people to help me out with it, but the current plan is to get back into writing out the models for the package and coding it up once PhD applications are all submitted (sometime in the beginning of 2025).</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="econ-thoughts"/><category term="tidy-tuesday"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I wanted to start off by saying that Github Co-Pilot is amazing. I’m not super sure about the specifics of what it trains on but it has to somehow look at my git tracked code and give suggestions based on my coding style which is just spectacular. Often times the most demoralizing part of doing a coding project is typing out tedious code that one knows how to write but just takes effort and unnessary mental energy (especially if there are some unintended bugs). Co-Pilot bypasses all of that with just one keystroke; more often than not the code that Co-Pilot writes is not buggy (especially if it’s something not particularly complicated). The greatest thing is that sure you can ask write out a detailed prompt in the chat window for AI to interpret and answer, but Co-Pilot also has an autocomplete feature where you can only write out the name of the function and it does the rest for you (sometimes it even knows what function you want to write next before you type out the name).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">summer of 2024</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/summer-of-2024/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="summer of 2024"/><published>2024-08-10T17:28:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-10T17:28:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/summer-of-2024</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/summer-of-2024/"><![CDATA[<p>The first thing I want to talk about is that I’ve made pretty significant progress on the TidyTuesday front. Turns out that having a very clearly defined project that works with data and nice APIs really gets me motivated to make progress on it. There are always more features and capabilities to add with these sorts of things, but I’m pretty sure I’ll be able to finish the baseline version that works with the Fred API by this weekend and get it up and running to be able to make my first renewed TidyTuesday post by next next Tuesday. Just as a reminder if you didn’t catch the last blog post, the idea is to renew the TidyTuesday series by running a random regression every day and reporting on one of the interesting ones each week; maybe there’s some cool interaction to discover (although very unlikely). I’m also using this as an opportunity to get some practice in writing code to compartmentalize and automatically generate chunks of reports in LaTeX where I only need to contribute to writing some qualitative color and everything else is already taken care of (something that’s a very helpful tool when working with products that are run repetitively with different data or small changes much like the work we do with forecasting on DSGE at the Fed).</p> <p>In other news, this summer is almost to an end. It has gone by both pretty quickly and gruelingly slow at times, but we are now entering quite the stressful era with PhD applications coming up soon. To be honest, I really don’t want to talk much about all the stressful stuff, so here are a few of the new restaurants and bakeries that I’ve been to over the summer that I want to highlight (these are all places in New York):</p> <ul> <li>Dominique Ansel</li> <li>Little Flower Cafe</li> <li>Win Son Bakery (can’t believe it took me this long to go here)</li> <li>NONONO</li> <li>Obica Mozzarella Bar</li> <li>Cafe China</li> <li>Glaze Teriyaki</li> <li>Cha Pa’s Noodles and Grill</li> </ul> <p>I’m not going to talk much about any of these right now, but there is a favorites in NYC so far post that is coming up as well. Along those lines, here are some places that are still on the list and I will be hitting sometime soon:</p> <ul> <li>Lucali’s</li> <li>Steve’s Authentic Key Lime Pie</li> <li>Birdbox (really curious to see if this dethrones Rowdy Rooster as my favorite fried chicken place)</li> </ul> <p>Finally, as a preface for next week, I’ll finally be talking about some of my NSF ideas and a really basic general setup for spatial general equilibrium models that is not necessarily what I’ll be using for NSF but something that may make its way into the eventual spatial-sims package (along with some more ideas about the purpose of the package now that I have a better grasp on the literature).</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal-updates"/><category term="the-pittsburgh-palate"/><category term="tidy-tuesday"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The first thing I want to talk about is that I’ve made pretty significant progress on the TidyTuesday front. Turns out that having a very clearly defined project that works with data and nice APIs really gets me motivated to make progress on it. There are always more features and capabilities to add with these sorts of things, but I’m pretty sure I’ll be able to finish the baseline version that works with the Fred API by this weekend and get it up and running to be able to make my first renewed TidyTuesday post by next next Tuesday. Just as a reminder if you didn’t catch the last blog post, the idea is to renew the TidyTuesday series by running a random regression every day and reporting on one of the interesting ones each week; maybe there’s some cool interaction to discover (although very unlikely). I’m also using this as an opportunity to get some practice in writing code to compartmentalize and automatically generate chunks of reports in LaTeX where I only need to contribute to writing some qualitative color and everything else is already taken care of (something that’s a very helpful tool when working with products that are run repetitively with different data or small changes much like the work we do with forecasting on DSGE at the Fed).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hello on Github! (and refurbishing TidyTuesday)</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/refurbishing-TidyTuesday/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hello on Github! (and refurbishing TidyTuesday)"/><published>2024-08-03T17:45:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-03T17:45:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/refurbishing-TidyTuesday</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/refurbishing-TidyTuesday/"><![CDATA[<p>I have not posted in quite a while and this is mostly because I have been migrating my old website to this new one (which is also thanks to another new friend)! There are still some formatting kinks I want to work out and I need to figure out how to add both a comments section and an email subscriber button, but this will be my website for a long while to come (I am, for the first time, actually quite satisfied with it except for some very minor formatting issues).</p> <p>We will be getting back into our regularly scheduled weekly posts now with a flavor towards stuff I’m learning or experiencing whilst working on NSF just to efficiently multitask (although that being said there are still a lot of post ideas I still have in store as well).</p> <p>One other thing that has been in the back of my mind for a long while is TidyTuesday; I basically only did one post and abandoned it right after that. I realized right after the first post back then that it was not worth the time commitment required to make a quality post week after week. As I’ve been uploading all the blogs back onto the new website and looking at the poor state of TidyTuesday, I remembered a conversation I had with a friend and work team member. We have this running joke about whenever we encounter a roadblock, the solution is to just “run a regression” as the empirical economists do. One day, somehow the conversation diverged to this as well, and we were making jokes about running random regressions one random timeseries. This is what I think I will turn TidyTuesday into: a script that runs automatically every day that picks two random timeseries from the plethora of data APIs and runs a regression between the two. Then every week I pick one of the seven that I found interesting and talk a little bit more about the relationship between the two timeseries.</p> <p>There are of course more details and functionalities I can add into the code to do this (such as picking some controls) but for now the project idea is just to do the automation and generate a systematic report each day (and then automatically push it to github). Regardless, I cannot promise much progress on this for a while between NSF and grad apps but do expect this to show its face by the end of the year.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal-updates"/><category term="tidy-tuesday"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have not posted in quite a while and this is mostly because I have been migrating my old website to this new one (which is also thanks to another new friend)! There are still some formatting kinks I want to work out and I need to figure out how to add both a comments section and an email subscriber button, but this will be my website for a long while to come (I am, for the first time, actually quite satisfied with it except for some very minor formatting issues).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the game theory of mutually assured destruction</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/the-game-theory-of-mutually-assured-destruction/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the game theory of mutually assured destruction"/><published>2024-06-23T21:36:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-23T21:36:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/the-game-theory-of-mutually-assured-destruction</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/the-game-theory-of-mutually-assured-destruction/"><![CDATA[<p>I have been getting a lot of ideas/questions from the Remembrance of Earth’s Past series. One of the concepts that shows up towards the end of the second book, The Dark Forest, and is discussed in a lot more detail in the third book, Death’s End, is the deterrence through mutually assured destruction or MAD.</p> <p>One quick tangent: I searched up what exactly the definition of MAD entails and although the definition of the terminology itself should apply, the term itself in the context of what it was made for applies specifically to mutually assured destruction through nuclear weapons with a first strike against a nation with second strike capabilities. So I’m not super sure if MAD the best term to describe what was happening in Death’s End since it was only one side threatening the destruction of both parties, in the book they call it simply “Dark Forest Deterrence” but for the sake of this post I’ll continue to call it MAD just because it does have logical parallels to the origin of the term (and also MAD is fewer characters to type out each time)</p> <p>In the book, the way MAD was threatened was through an “universal broadcast” that Earth could send out that included the located of the alien species’ star system and since humankind’s system and Trisolaris’ system were so close together that this would cause other alien species to discover the solar system as well. The reason why discovery was so scary was because this series ascribes to the “Dark Forest” explanation as to why alien civilizations were so hard to find: that all the surviving civilizations were very technologically advanced groups who distrusted every other civilization by default and operated under a “shoot on sight” protocol so broadcasting one’s location would get them immediately annihilated. In the case of Earth, this broadcast system was under control of a single individual. This, of course, was an immense responsibility since they were in control of the fate of two civilizations. So, in picking who that individual would be, one would have to make sure that it would be a person who would not activate the signal needlessly, but also give the impression that they would activate the signal when being attacked.</p> <p>This is a very similar issue to what the US had faced during the Cold War. Whenever I watch documentaries or listen to podcasts on the subject, they always talk about how there was so much research being done on this MAD-related game theory problem. For most of my life prior, I always thought that this was really silly given that my impression was that game theory was one of those simple 2x2 games. In retrospect now, I realize that to truly model the complexity of what is going on and include more nuances specific to the situation, you have to consider the exact mechanisms by which a MAD situation would be activated. Questions such as: who exactly has control of the launch, are they likely to retaliate even if they already know they are doomed, are there multiple people involved in the launching of nuclear weapons, how do you maximize the perception of one’s threat against their opponent without sacrificing other things? All these are questions that can be incorporated into a model that make the question a bit more interesting than one of those “2x2 Find the Nash Equilibria” games.</p> <p>I’ll detail one such model soon, but just for some context we can make to the archetypical 2x2 we see in high school Econ classes (note: that most of these changes are taken as part of a standard model in game theory in the literature, I’m not too read up on it so I may be missing a few key components):</p> <ul> <li>Tack on some functional structure for the probabilities that both the first and second strike of MAD are activated.</li> <li>Introduce multiple actions (with complete destruction being minus infinity utility). One can even make it an action that lies on some continuous domain instead of discrete choices.</li> <li>For games with sequential actions, we can represent the problem as nested games with each action taken further filtering the state spacetakes.</li> </ul> <p>With all that in mind, let’s try to construct a model for a Cold War-type situation between two world powers.</p> <iframe src="/assets/pdf/modeling-MAD.pdf" width="100%" height="1000px"></iframe>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="econ-thoughts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Note, Some spoilers for the Remembrance of Earth's Past series]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">first food post pt. 2</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/first-food-post-pt2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="first food post pt. 2"/><published>2024-06-11T19:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-11T19:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/first-food-post-pt2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/first-food-post-pt2/"><![CDATA[<p>I’m still cooking up another game theory-related post that will take a bit more time to finish (and so here is another Pittsburgh related food post). The last post covered only some of the neighborhoods in Pittsburgh, so here is the other batch of places that the typical CMU student only goes to sometimes.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Strip District</strong>: This neighborhood is well known for the food scene and the grocery stores. When I lived in North Oakland, I would occasionally walk here (which, in retrospect, was a very sketchy path). I used to go to the Strip District a bit during freshman year since this is where the Red Cross office in Pittsburgh. <ul> <li><em>Restaurant</em>: Coop de Ville (although I have not bought food from this place in person) is my absolute favorite takeout fried chicken place. I’ve gotten GrubHub deliveries from there many times.</li> <li><em>Coffee</em>: De Fer Coffee and Tea happens to be my favorite coffee shop to work at in Pittsburgh just because of the vibe and the ability to take a nice walk in a cool area afterward.</li> <li><em>Misc</em>: Klavon’s, which unfortunately may not be open anymore, is my favorite ice cream parlor in Pittsburgh. I happen to be a fan of sundaes and Klavon’s is miles above the competition. Also, Macaroni Company is a cool grocery store.</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Downtown</strong>: I rarely went downtown sophomore and junior year (because of the pandemic) and so I didn’t have as much exposure to this area of Pittsburgh as I did with many of the others. One factor that did help me get more familiar with the area was that I interned at PNC the summer before my senior year, which, in addition to being able to go out for lunch, introduced me to a lot of people who also had their lists of Pittsburgh favorites. <ul> <li><em>Coffee</em>: I never managed to go to Gasoline Street Coffee Company until after I had graduated, but it has a nice vibe (they have a chess board) and has pretty good coffee.</li> <li><em>Lunch Places</em>: Arrepittas has a filling combo platter that would always satisfy my craving for Latin American food. Sree’s Foods, on the other hand, was one of the few Indian places I enjoyed in Pittsburgh. It was started by this couple from Hyderabad and I feel like they would give me a little extra food when I spoke in Telugu.</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Lawrenceville</strong>: This is a neighborhood that is known for some refined restaurants. I’ve only been here a few times so I can’t speak to much. <ul> <li><em>Restaurant</em>: Picolo forno is a nice Italian place; can’t say much more than I enjoyed my experience there. Condado’s on the other hand is a Pittsburgh classic (known for its fusion tacos) and whenever I get takeout from Condados’s it’s always from this specific location.</li> <li><em>Coffee</em>: I have surprisingly been to a handful of coffee shops here but Espresso a Mano stands above the rest.</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Southside</strong>: Although there are a few spots that I absolutely adore from this neighborhood I’ve actually only visited in person two-three times. <ul> <li><em>Restaurant</em>: The place I’ve gotten the most takeout from in Pittsburgh is Cilantro and Ajo (I don’t even remember how many times now). The plantains side dish is by far the best plantains I have ever eaten and their cilantro crema is also absolutely amazing.</li> <li><em>Coffee</em>: Delanie’s Coffee is my pick for the Southside. Not going to lie this is the only coffee place I have gotten coffee from in Southside but it was still pretty decent.</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Northside</strong>: Most people don’t even know the name of this neighborhood other than the fact that it’s home to The Mattress Factory. I can’t say I’m much better to be honest though since this is the neighborhood that I’ve been to the least (although I did know the name). <ul> <li><em>Restaurant/Coffee</em>: 40 North at Alphabet City is the only place I’ve been that I feel is worth putting on this list. There’s an attached bookshop, and bookshop food combined places are always pretty cool.</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Bloomfield</strong>: This neighborhood in my opinion is a weird in between going places neighborhood and so I’ve grouped an interesting swath of area into this place. <ul> <li><em>Restaurant</em>: The first time I went to Apteka I had an amazing time. The second time I will say was not nearly as good of a time as the first and so I’m conflicted since I came out of the place the first time thinking that it was the best restaurant in Pittsburgh and the second time thinking it was subpar. Regardless it’s a place that has to be mentioned.</li> <li><em>Coffee</em>: Ineffable Ca Phe is a Vietnamese place that, in addition to coffee, also sells Bahn Mi’s. It also has a lot of space and quite a few outlets so nice place to camp out to get some work done.</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Other mentions</strong>: Wheelfish is the best barbeque place I have been to in Pittsburgh (although it is in some suburban neighborhood that requires a car to get to). The Exchange is actually on the CMU campus and one of the places I think 90% of CMU students can agree upon as being good.</li> </ul> <p>So that’s my big list of places I wanted to write down somewhere and share. I will also reiterate my list is from the perspective of a college student who is on a budget 99% of the time. I know for a fact that there are some places (especially Downtown, West Southside, and the Strip District) where some better-endowed people tend to go. Regardless I’m confident that anyone will have a good time at each of the places on my list.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="the-pittsburgh-palate"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’m still cooking up another game theory-related post that will take a bit more time to finish (and so here is another Pittsburgh related food post). The last post covered only some of the neighborhoods in Pittsburgh, so here is the other batch of places that the typical CMU student only goes to sometimes.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">first food post pt. 1</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/first-food-post-pt1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="first food post pt. 1"/><published>2024-06-02T13:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-02T13:20:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/first-food-post-pt1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/first-food-post-pt1/"><![CDATA[<p>I did promise a few posts back that I would start to post a bit more about food. Cooking and learning about (and eating of course) food are pretty big parts of my life in terms of interests. It developed a lot from being in a family/extended family that values food a lot as well and because of that, I watched a lot of food-related shows during high school/college (which brought about the interest in learning about food from different cultures and the basics of cooking techniques). Even now, although I don’t watch many shows related to food, there are a lot of YouTubers I watch and some books that I enjoy reading.</p> <p>That all in mind, I happen to consider myself to be quite the connoisseur of restaurants in Pittsburgh (well a connoisseur of all the college student budget-friendly places in Pittsburgh at least); a proxy of how much time I spent in the city and the one summer I spent there basically alone. Pittsburgh is interesting because each of the neighborhoods are clearly culturally distinctive (much like NYC and very much unlike Dallas) but it’s not as big as other big American cities. The summer I spent in Pittsburgh alone I made it a personal goal to explore a different neighborhood each weekend and I have some recommendations of things to do and places to eat at in each neighborhood that I wanted to share. I will say that there are a few neighborhoods that I didn’t include but that’s either most likely because I didn’t spend that much time there or because there isn’t anything that comes to mind to take note of.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Shadyside</strong>: I lived here my senior year and had a really nice routine each weekend where I would work/read in a coffee shop and then take a nice walk to get groceries. I still visited this area a lot throughout my four years in Pittsburgh regardless and I’ve basically eaten at every place here. <ul> <li><em>Coffee Shop</em>: Jitters Cafe is a must. This is where I got into my weekend coffee, croissant, and a book/journal routine.</li> <li><em>Bakery</em>: Georgie’s Corner Cafe is a little on the higher end for a bakery in Pittsburgh for a college student, but it definitely merits multiple visits since each one of their baked goods and breakfast items is so good.</li> <li><em>Restaurant</em>: This is a bit hard to choose from since Walnut St. is such an iconic place for restaurants in Pittsburgh and I’ve been to many of them many times but at the end of the day I have to highlight Café Moulin and Mercurio’s as my personal favorites.</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>North Oakland</strong>: I spent basically 2.5 years in North Oakland so this is the place I know the best. That being said, especially senior year once the effects of the pandemic lifted off a bit more, it feels like the turnover of restaurants coming and going is pretty high here. <ul> <li><em>Cafe/Bakery</em>: Sidecar (as it’s called now, it’s been through a lot of name changes) is the companion cafe of Butterjoint (a restaurant) which I actually don’t like as much as I do the cafe.</li> <li><em>Restaurant</em>: In my opinion, this area is really good for college students. Both EGE Mediterranean (the smell coming out of that place as you’re walking back after a tough day is impossible to resist) and TW Kitchen are really good quality. Most places in this area are small family-owned type places where people remember your face and I liked that a lot.</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p><strong>CMU / Craig St.</strong>: I mostly added this section because I feel like Craig St. needed a section of its own. My friend group liked EatUnique a lot (to be honest, it’s only financially feasible as a freshman with a lot of flex money). There are a lot of other cool places but I think I’m doing a disservice if I don’t put Chipotle on here just because of how many times I went to that Chipotle (even if they do skimp on the chicken)</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Central Oakland</strong>: I’m grouping all of the UPitt area into this. I haven’t been to any cafes here but there are so many restaurants here its hard to keep track. This is a really lesser known place and is unfortunately closed now (its literally in a basement) but I think I have to give an honorable mention to Pie Express. The quality wasn’t really top notch or close to top notch but they had this $5 personal pizza deal during the pandemic that was amazing. Other than that Milkshake Factory and Roots are two Pittsburgh only places that I’ve visited many a times.</p> </li> <li><strong>Squirrel Hill</strong>: Like Central Oakland, this place is a big CMU hub because a lot of people live here. Squirrel Hill is most iconic for all the Asian restaurants here but also one thing to note is that I’m grouping in a vast swath of area without making a difference between North, Central/East, and South Squirel Hill. <ul> <li><em>Cafe</em>: For drinks personal favorite is Dobra Tea. Its kind of bougie in its seating area but its a really cool vibe and they take their tea very seriously.</li> <li><em>Bakery</em>: I have never heard anyone at CMU even mention Five Points Bakery which is such a travesty because IMO its miles ahead of all the other bakery competition in Pittsburgh. There are so many unique and well-made items here that you have to visit multiple times.</li> <li><em>Restaurant</em>: I’m going to have to mention all Cafe 33, Sichuan Gourmet, and Kiin Lao. Kiin Lao and Sichuan Gourtet are the places that got me into liking Thai and Chinese cuisine respectively and are both places I’ve been to quite often.</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>East Liberty</strong>: I feel like this neighborhood is known primarily among freshman for having a Target and it was the first area I visited just because of this reason. <ul> <li><em>Cafe</em>: I feel like Margaux isn’t super well known among CMU students but man, do they have really cool desserts.</li> <li><em>Restaurant</em>: Noodlehead to me feels like an iconic Pittsburgh place. I have no idea why and when I ask other CMU students, the sentiment is rarely reciprocated. I think its mostly because it and Choolah were one of the first few places I ate out in Pittsburgh.</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>Next week we’ll cover each of the lesser well known places for CMU students.</p> <ul> <li>Strip District</li> <li>Downtown</li> <li>Lawrenceville</li> <li>Southside</li> <li>Northside</li> <li>Bloomfield</li> <li>Waterfront</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="the-pittsburgh-palate"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I did promise a few posts back that I would start to post a bit more about food. Cooking and learning about (and eating of course) food are pretty big parts of my life in terms of interests. It developed a lot from being in a family/extended family that values food a lot as well and because of that, I watched a lot of food-related shows during high school/college (which brought about the interest in learning about food from different cultures and the basics of cooking techniques). Even now, although I don’t watch many shows related to food, there are a lot of YouTubers I watch and some books that I enjoy reading.]]></summary></entry></feed>