<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-12-29T23:22:08+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Pranay Gundam</title><entry><title type="html">Food of Southwest National Parks Trip 2025</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2025/food-southwest-national-parks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Food of Southwest National Parks Trip 2025"/><published>2025-12-26T16:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-26T16:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2025/food-southwest-national-parks</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2025/food-southwest-national-parks/"><![CDATA[<p>Went on a National Parks Trip across the Southwest (Death Valley, Grand Canyon, Petrified Forest, Saguaro), and here are all the notable food places we went to.</p> <p><em>Las Vegas</em></p> <ul> <li><strong>Cafe Lola</strong> : It was decent food but hella expensive. $12 for a latte is next level of crazy to me.</li> <li><strong>Momofuku</strong> : The Spicy Miso Ramen was good for sure. A definite 7/10. The cost-to-value ratio though for most items at this place did not seem worth. I do understand the Las Vegas scene encourages a certain type of menu, but I personally would have really preferred something more akin to the New York menu offering. I will also note that they partner with the Chase Sapphire Lounge and their food there in the airport lounge was a nice touch (even though I did prefer food in other Chase Sapphire Lounges in other airports).</li> <li><strong>Sticky Toffee Pudding at Hell’s Kitchen</strong> : I had a massive urge to eat sticky toffee pudding. Gordon Ramsey’s sticky toffee pudding in Hell’s Kitchen is definitely iconic and this dessert did hit the spot. We also managed to just walk in and instantly get a spot in at the bar which is an additional plus point.</li> <li><strong>Wynn Buffet</strong> : I wanted to experience a buffet in Vegas. I had too many dishes to go through them all but the final takeaway is that it was a cool experience and a lot of food but I likely won’t be doing something like that again unless there is truly something unique to the buffet.</li> <li><strong>La Strega</strong> : We went here on the last night of our visit and it was a satisfying end foodwise. They had this unique focaccia with halves of grapes stuck into it that was really nice paired with some simple olive oil and salt. We also got a grilled artichoke appetizer that was spectacular. The mains were not exemplary by any means but still par for the course in total. Specifically, we got an orecchiette pasta that had a light umami mushroom sauce which had a nice al dente bite. Good, but not as wowing as the appetizers. The pizza (alla norma) that we got, however, I was a little disappointed with. It could have definitely used a bit more time in the oven to crisp up more which I am not sure if a conscious choice because they didn’t want to overcook the toppings or if that’s just what they tend to do with their pizzas but either way it could have done with a couple more minutes in the oven. The waitresses and general service staff were quite friendly.</li> </ul> <p><em>Flagstaff</em></p> <ul> <li><strong>Atria</strong> : Boy oh boy was this quite the surprise. We came here on a whim just because another restaurant called Fat Olive had a long wait time (also on a sidenote, Flagstaff, Arizona has a crazy food scene relative to what I was expecting). Before I dive into each dish specifically, to set expectations, this is by far my favorite Contemporary American restaurant of all time and I will undoubtedly be coming back here every time I visit the Grand Canyon. It beats out All Saints (which is a restaurant in Minneapolis that I love and will soon be writing about on the blog) and even my experience at Gramercy Tavern in NYC. I will definitely be fair and be explicit about the fact that Contemporary American is not a cuisine that I often frequent, but Atria is setting a high bar even across cuisines.</li> </ul> <p>Starting with the <em>bread</em> . It was nothing too crazy flavor wise. Just wonderfully baked and paired with a nice berry butter.</p> <p>Next for the <em>beets</em> . I’ve had a similar dish at “All Saints” in Minneapolis; both dishes try to accomplish the same thing with regards to highlighting beets but the flavor profile of everything else on the plate is different. At All Saints it is very acidic but here at Atria it is paired with some more umami coming from tahini and a firmer goat cheese instead of a more flimsy burrata at All Saints’. I don’t think I have a strict preference between the two but the dish at Atria was a nice change of pace.</p> <p>There is not a single person I know who doesn’t like filled pasta. The <em>squash agnolotti</em> was also definitely up there in terms of a good filled pasta and all the components came together quite nicely.</p> <p>I really enjoyed this <em>Cacio e pepe</em> . I’ve never seen people use tagliatellini (that’s what they call it) so it felt like more of an Asian-style noodle but cooked al dente. I feel, however, that actually contributed more to my enjoyment because I like experiencing the differences between simple pastas using different pasta types.</p> <p>Finally, the least enjoyed dish out of everything was the <em>roasted squash</em> . It was certainly perfectly cooked/grilled, but my main gripe with cooking large vegetables in American restaurants is that it’s handled like a meat. I find, however, that meats need less seasoning to bring out flavor and a big chunk of squash necessarily requires that the eater compose every forkful perfectly with all the side accoutrements else the bite ends up lacking enough flavor. That being said, we did enjoy it as a whole but definitely would have chosen something else on the menu if given the choice again.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/food-of-southwest-national-parks/bread_atria-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/food-of-southwest-national-parks/bread_atria-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/food-of-southwest-national-parks/bread_atria-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/food-of-southwest-national-parks/bread_atria.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/food-of-southwest-national-parks/beets_atria-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/food-of-southwest-national-parks/beets_atria-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/food-of-southwest-national-parks/beets_atria-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/food-of-southwest-national-parks/beets_atria.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/food-of-southwest-national-parks/agnolotti_atria-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/food-of-southwest-national-parks/agnolotti_atria-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/food-of-southwest-national-parks/agnolotti_atria-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/food-of-southwest-national-parks/agnolotti_atria.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/food-of-southwest-national-parks/cacioepepe_atria-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/food-of-southwest-national-parks/cacioepepe_atria-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/food-of-southwest-national-parks/cacioepepe_atria-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/food-of-southwest-national-parks/cacioepepe_atria.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/food-of-southwest-national-parks/squash_atria-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/food-of-southwest-national-parks/squash_atria-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/food-of-southwest-national-parks/squash_atria-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/food-of-southwest-national-parks/squash_atria.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Food from Atria, from left to right: Bread, Roasted Beets, Squash Agnolotti, Cacio e Pepe, Roasted Squash </div> <p>I will end this section about Atria with two caveats about my review. The first is that I didn’t have any meat dish which spans most of the menu. I’ll be sure to try more next time I go, but the meat dishes of people next to me looked good as well. Second, they reused a lot of the same components for the vegetarian dishes. There was a lot of Macha salsa and squash puree across everything that we ate and I felt it would have gotten a little tiring if we had a few more dishes with them. As a whole though, this was the best meal of the trip and my best meal at a restaurant in a while.</p> <ul> <li><strong>High Country Motor Lodge</strong> : This was our hotel in Flagstaff but they also had a lobby cafe. The vibe of the hotel itself was “an old Route 66 motel taken over and refurbished by current day hip millennials” which is an aesthetic I did enjoy. The food matched that vibe as well. We got a breakfast sandwich and an avocado toast, neither of which I can complain about much. They were decent.</li> </ul> <p><em>Tucson</em></p> <ul> <li><strong>La Frida</strong> : We waited for two hours for a seat at this place. They have no reservation system so it’s all walk-in leading to a massive crowd of people sitting outside the restaurant. Was the two-hour wait worth it? Not at all. Not saying that the restaurant was bad, they had some really nice dishes such as the elote appetizer below, but I have historically had an issue with the dryness of the enchilada filling. Not sure if this is just me or if that’s just how enchiladas are, but I was expecting something different from this restaurant. The one thing that they seemed to be doing with most tables, however, that was quite cool was that they had a bowl of chips, queso, and salsa waiting for you before you got seated. A lot of restaurants do give a free dish such as bread or chips and salsa but very few actually have something waiting for you before you even get seated. There are of course issues regarding allergies, but I think this is such a powerful small detail that immediately sets the hospitality tone for the customer.</li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/food-of-southwest-national-parks/costilla-de-elote-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/food-of-southwest-national-parks/costilla-de-elote-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/food-of-southwest-national-parks/costilla-de-elote-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/food-of-southwest-national-parks/costilla-de-elote.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Costilla de Elote (after having been partially eaten) </div> <p><em>Phoenix</em></p> <ul> <li><strong>Casa Corazon</strong> : Above, I talked about my gripe with the enchiladas. I got some enchiladas here as well but unlike all my past experiences, these were phenomenal. The filling had some cheese in it, along with the chicken, and this made all the difference. I’m not sure if this is traditional or not, but I sure as hell enjoyed my meal a lot more. Otherwise this restaurant had a self serve salsa station that was cool but we didn’t order much of anything else so not much more to report on.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="the-pittsburgh-palate"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I think I'm going to call this series the 'Food of ...' series]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">soccer thoughts pt.1</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2025/soccer-thoughts-pt1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="soccer thoughts pt.1"/><published>2025-12-05T10:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-05T10:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2025/soccer-thoughts-pt1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2025/soccer-thoughts-pt1/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://pranaygundam.substack.com/p/soccer-thoughts-pt1">Link to the substack post.</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal-updates"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Link to the substack post.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a love letter to nyc</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2025/a-love-letter-to-nyc/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a love letter to nyc"/><published>2025-08-27T19:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-27T19:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2025/a-love-letter-to-nyc</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2025/a-love-letter-to-nyc/"><![CDATA[<p>I came to nyc a skeptic. Growing up in a Dallas suburb makes one accustomed to a certain spacious life style and convenience of transportation by car. It’s a feeling of supremacy that leads to statements like “I would never want to settle down in a big city like New York.”</p> <p>Now that I’ve moved out, however, I feel quite conflicted. I only lived in nyc for a grand total of 734 days, but I am now connected to it in a way that I would have never thought I would. I used to make fun of the common stereotype of people who move to the city and make cliché claims about how they fell in love with the city and couldn’t think of a life outside of it. While I definitely can imagine a life outside of nyc, I leave it with an impression of nyc being the ultimate city. It’s as if most other places I visit now have lost their luster and end up underwhelming. There’s a big asterisk next to every city I visit that says “this is no New York”. Of course there are many pros and cons to living in nyc, but it is damn hard to find a place that checks as many boxes. One of these boxes is neighborhood identity. I haven’t lived in a large number of places so far, but one thing that I deeply enjoy in a city is neighborhood identity.</p> <p>Dallas and most of its surrounding suburbs didn’t have any sense of identity and Pittsburgh actually had a decent amount for the size of city that it is, but nyc is the king of all cities when it comes to neighborhood identity. Each community has naturally been built around either some ethnic identity or a theme. For neighborhoods in Manhattan, even though this core identity has shifted over time for neighborhoods (as rent prices have gone up and those core groups of people that created the neighborhood identity have moved further deeper into Queens and Brooklyn) the qualitative distinctions are clear through the various restaurants, establishments, and community leaders that make up each given neighborhood. I’ve realized that what I want most in a long term place to live is both somewhere that promotes an active lifestyle and also is enjoyable to explore where each of the neighborhoods has a distinct identity. It’s true that a cushy settled down life in nyc is very expensive but it is quite evocative for the dreamers like myself.</p> <p>The delay in emotionally connecting to nyc came as a surprise to me because frankly, I love cities. I love the way you can look at another person’s face and dream about all the experiences that they have gone through in their lives, I love the way that you can sit on a bench and try to reminisce about everything that has happened on that sidewalk over the past hundreds of years, and I love how you can contemplate about the micro interactions between people and communities from the physical real-world ebbs and flows of a neighborhood. That’s actually how I originally got into economics. The same way one can use physics to understand the way a river carves into the surrounding environment over time, I view economics as a tool to understand the dynamics of humans and the structures that they build; a tool to help understand why cities change the way that they do; an instrument that helps you visualize the latent structure behind those timelapses of satellite images.</p> <p>I’ve moved to Minneapolis now for grad school. It will be quite the change from the past two years but a change that I am very much looking forward to.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal-updates"/><category term="econ-thoughts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I came to nyc a skeptic. Growing up in a Dallas suburb makes one accustomed to a certain spacious life style and convenience of transportation by car. It’s a feeling of supremacy that leads to statements like “I would never want to settle down in a big city like New York.”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the career rat race</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2025/the-career-rat-race/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the career rat race"/><published>2025-06-28T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-28T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2025/the-career-rat-race</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2025/the-career-rat-race/"><![CDATA[<p>One of the most relevant issues that I have faced since starting schooling is the seemingly endless rat race that is one’s educational and career pursuits. As a kid growing up in a run of the mill middle class suburb, this race began early—with kids being sorted into different levels of math classes and reading groups in elementary school, to maximizing the number of AP classes one could take at increasingly younger ages. What was once something rare like traveling from our Junior High campus to the Senior High campus to take AP Chemistry every day soon became a norm in the later years and the cycle of continuously trying to gain the upper leg keeps accelerating. I’ve seen a lot of this behavior now too in the context of economics graduate applications.</p> <p>At a purely reactionary and emotional level, this rat race strikes me as unfair. Why is it that the new generation is forced to deal with an increasingly competitive environment that always demands more effort? Why were academics of earlier generations seemingly able to lead less hyper-focused academic lives and end up in the place that they are right now? It seems as if it is increasingly becoming the case that to reach the same goals, one has to be more deliberate, more singularly driven, all from an earlier age than those that have come before. Surely there has to be some limiting factor other than age for what experience one can squish in to gain an upper hand later on.</p> <p>On the other hand, from the lens of an economist: I wonder more so about how thJust for those who don’t know, predoc programs are typically 1-2 year positions at research institutions that serve as a way to build up research experience prior to joining a PhD program.e race got to where it is now and what equilibrium it will tend itself towards rather than if it’s fair or not. Since the economics phd application process is what I have experienced most recently I’ll focus on that, but a lot of points have parallels in other fields as well. The push and pull dynamics here at play seem straightforward; the demand for economics phd degrees is pretty high (I’m not so sure about the trend of the demand but I would like to say it is at the very least not decreasing) relative to supply so there is a pushing force on applicants to boost their resume relative to others, and the supply of such opportunities to gain experience before entering the applicant pool rises to meet that demand as well in the form of masters programs or predocs. It is quite uncommon nowadays for a student to gain admission into an econ phd program without having done either a predoc or a masters and not so uncommon for someone to have done multiple predocs/masters<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. The main pull force that are the opportunity costs: these pre-PhD experiences take time, cost money, and delay higher future earnings. This model so far incentivizes a world where people who have a lot of time, money, and industry know-how to succeed. People who have no time or money constraints can take the time to build their experience before applying to phd programs, and people who know already how academia works can plan out their path from an early age. Qualitatively, this usually means socio-economically privileged groups of people. I would argue, however, that the real world has another pull force: the cost of the homogeneity of applicant pool. I don’t think we have seen any specific costs that I can quantitatively point out to just yet but the main idea is that as people are forced to focus on similar experiences and also come from similar backgrounds they tend to think similarly as a result. Homogenous groups of thought, in the realm of academia, may be detrimental to the rate of making drastic breakthroughs.</p> <p>Now that we have discussed the push forces that incentivize applicants to gather more experience before applying to PhD programs and the pull forces that incentivize applicants to just shoot off an application, I think it would be interesting to have a discussion about how we could quantitatively wean out the magnitude of these effects to see how important they are and make some predictions about where this “rat race” will head in the future. The first step to doing so is writing out some sort of model that spells out how each of these forces effect the chance of being admitted and the preferences of a given applicant.</p> <ol> <li>To begin, let’s say that the applicant generally prefers to start their PhD earlier rather than later but also benefits from entering their PhD with some level of experience but there are diminishing returns (meaning that getting 2 years of experience is still better than getting 1 year of experience but not more than the difference between 1 and 0 years of experience).</li> <li>Let’s say that each year after graduating, the applicant makes the choice between trying out their hand in the application process, using the year to get more econ experience, or using the year to get more life experience (i.e. a not strictly academic economics related job).</li> <li>The utility that the applicants achieve in this model can be summarized as two-fold. On one hand they experience monetary utility, so supposedly choosing one year of gaining life experience would give them more money that year than choosing one year of an econ experience or even choosing to apply to grad school if they are already quite old and won’t benefit much from the increased lifetime earnings after grad school. Second, applicants supposedly also have some desire to have a career in economics so they also gain some personal utility from being in grad school.</li> <li>The final component is the probability that an applicant makes it into a PhD program. Depends on how much econ experience they have (the more econ experience, the high chance they will make into a program), how much innate ability they have (this basically encompasses how likely they are to get into a program without any econ or life experience, just how cracked they are), and how much life experience they have (life experience does contribute positively to the chance of getting into a program but this is always less than a econ experience even if a very homogenous class increases the effectiveness of life experience).</li> </ol> <p>To summarize, our model focuses on the agent’s (applicant’s) choices throughout their post grad life until retirement. Each year, the applicant is faced with three choices, either to shoot in a PhD Application, spend the year pursuing some economics experience, or spend the year pursuing some other job outside of economics. They get the most monetary compensation if they decide to pursue a job outside of economics, second most if they pursue some economics experience, and the least if they send in a PhD application; the utility for personal satisfaction goes the opposite direction. The probability that get into a PhD program if they choose to submit an application is based on how much life experience they have, how much econ experience they have, how much inherent potential they have, and the homogeneity of the existing phd classes (the more homogenous the class the more life experience will increase the probability of success).</p> <p>There are a few areas in the model described above that feel a bit iffy to me but I like this representation as a starting point, feel free to comment below or shoot me a text if you think of any driving questions/assumptions you think need to be answered. For those more inclined to look at the model described above in specific mathematical terms, you can refer to the pdf below. Ultimately, the original question I had asked was how far will the rat race go. You can answer that using this model from the perspective of an individual who isn’t fully noticing what’s going on around them in that this model doesn’t incorporate any concepts of agents strategically reacting to others based on how many years of life or econ experience they have for example.</p> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Just for those who don’t know, predoc programs are typically 1-2 year positions at research institutions that serve as a way to build up research experience prior to joining a PhD program. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="econ-thoughts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[One of the most relevant issues that I have faced since starting schooling is the seemingly endless rat race that is one’s educational and career pursuits. As a kid growing up in a run of the mill middle class suburb, this race began early—with kids being sorted into different levels of math classes and reading groups in elementary school, to maximizing the number of AP classes one could take at increasingly younger ages. What was once something rare like traveling from our Junior High campus to the Senior High campus to take AP Chemistry every day soon became a norm in the later years and the cycle of continuously trying to gain the upper leg keeps accelerating. I’ve seen a lot of this behavior now too in the context of economics graduate applications.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">getting better at soccer</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2025/getting-better-at-soccer/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="getting better at soccer"/><published>2025-05-31T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-31T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2025/getting-better-at-soccer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2025/getting-better-at-soccer/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve mentioned this on the blog before, but one of the best things about moving to NYC for me has been being able to play soccer again. There was a tournament that had been running over the past few months, and it just wrapped up — our team came in second (after a grueling 3–2 loss in the finals). I ended up winning the golden boot with 14 goals and I actually learned a lot about both soccer and myself along the way.</p> <p>Before coming to NYC, I had basically quit playing soccer by the end of 10th grade. This was a significant decision, given that I’d been playing since 1st grade and had even reached the highest non-academy league level in Dallas during 8th and 9th grade. There was some sort of national ranking system (which, to be honest, I’m not entirely sure how it worked) that placed our team somewhere around 100th in the U.S. Despite playing at that level, I don’t think I was actually very good. I had made it there by relying on a mix of raw athleticism and the leftover confidence I had from my early, non-competitive days as a striker. That was enough to get me in, but nowhere near enough to keep me there.</p> <p>I hadn’t developed the habit of practicing on my own, or of watching and thinking about the sport off the field. I really enjoyed soccer as a kid, and that enjoyment was what kept me playing. But once I reached that higher level, a combination of an uninspiring coach and a socially distant team stripped away the childlike fun that had kept me going. With that joy gone, I had no motivation to work on or even think about soccer outside of practice.</p> <p>As an aside, it feels like many immigrant Indian families discourage working out, so I also lost my natural physical edge and speed advantage as other kids trained harder. All of this added up to what I now recognize as the worst possible mindset for a soccer player — especially a striker. I had no confidence. I was afraid of receiving the ball, I positioned myself only to chase through balls instead of trying to control the game, and I never socially connected with my teammates, which meant there was no mutual trust. I eventually stopped playing because soccer had become completely disconnected from the reasons I had enjoyed and excelled at it in the first place. Other interests like debate and orchestra — where I connected with people much more easily — started to take over.</p> <p>Of course, we can’t change the past, and things unfolded the way they did. Still, I can’t help but wonder how it might have turned out if even one factor had been different. The fact remains: I did quit, and I’ve made peace with that. But since then, I’ve undergone a lot of social, mental, and physical growth — and that has made my return to soccer incredibly rewarding.</p> <p>Socially, I’ve matured simply by getting older and learning to connect with all kinds of people despite our backgrounds or interests. Physically, I’ve started going to the gym and learned a lot about flexibility and strength training. Mentally — and this might sound unusual — a big part of my change has come from the anime Blue Lock. It’s about a youth soccer training camp in Japan focused solely on developing elite strikers. Each character has their own strengths and weaknesses, but what resonated most with me was the main character’s mindset. He starts far from the best player in the camp, but he builds a strong sense of self-confidence and works hard to analyze his own game. His main strength is understanding what conditions give him the highest chance of scoring — and then actively creating those conditions. Watching that show helped me realize that if I want to get good again and truly enjoy the game, I need to shift my mentality away from fear and toward the belief that every play will be better with me involved. The more I believe that, the more others believe it — and the more it becomes true.</p> <p>I know I still have plenty of strengths and weaknesses. I’m decent with my feet and can make good passes, though others are definitely better in those areas. And I’m no longer the “fast kid,” which was basically my whole identity before 9th grade. But I’ve discovered two main strengths: first, the ability to think critically about how to adapt my playstyle in order to win, and second, the ability to place the ball precisely where I want — whether in shooting or playmaking.</p> <p>A great example of these two strengths coming together is the way I’ve changed my shooting in our work league. Scoring in that league is tough because the goals posts are small. Most persons’ shots, even if they’re on target, end up bouncing off the keeper. But I’ve found that when I have the time, taking an extra half-second to analyze the defenders and pick out the more open top corner dramatically increases my conversion rate. This strategy has paid off in both pickup games and league matches. I also think I’m getting better at identifying how to shut down individual players — though coming up with strategies to shut down entire teams is still something I need to work on.</p> <p>All of these elements came together during the FED tournament. On paper, our team didn’t look like the strongest, but we had excellent chemistry. We pulled off a few great offensive plays where our teamwork really clicked, but more importantly, our playstyles meshed well. We could park the bus when needed and were very effective on the counterattack.</p> <p>That said, I still have a long way to go — especially outside the indoor 4v4 format of the FED. I need to focus on drills and hone the fundamentals, and I have big plans to do just that once I move to Minneapolis. I’m currently playing in an outdoor 7v7 league, and it hasn’t been going great. Some of the problems are obvious: my fitness (and that of my team) is clearly below the average level of our opponents. But I’ve also noticed other areas for personal improvement. For one, the format is different — no offsides and smaller goals. I’ve learned that fast, low shots to the corners are more effective than lofted shots to the top corners, which are easier for keepers to save because of the goal’s lower height. My positioning is also an issue. I know it’s tough when you’re joining an unfamiliar team, especially one that’s already established — you just get fewer touches. But I’ve noticed myself slipping back into the mindset I had in middle and high school: not being proactive about putting myself in positions where I become the obvious passing option. I need to consciously work on positioning and get a better sense of spatial awareness in this 7v7 format, which I know will come with time and repetition.</p> <p>I’ll be leaving NYC in a few months and moving to Minneapolis. I plan not only to continue my soccer journey but to level up. NYC’s leagues are fairly decentralized, but Minneapolis seems to have one centralized, competitive summer league organized by skill level. The top division is apparently made up of recent Division 1 college players. I’m nowhere near that level right now, but I think setting concrete targets is important, so my goal is to play in that top division for at least a year while I’m doing my PhD. More broadly, I want to make sure I’m playing regularly — at least one session a week, whether pickup or in a league — in addition to my other fitness goals.</p> <p>One last thing I’ve been thinking about is the use of quantitative methods in soccer. Everyone knows about Moneyball and the rise of analytics in baseball. But baseball is a much more static sport with well-defined game states — like who’s on base and who’s batting — which makes it easier to model. Football has some structure, but team-based sports like basketball and soccer are much more fluid, which makes it harder to analyze what actions a coach should direct their players to take at any given moment. Soccer is even more complex than basketball in this regard — more players on the field, a larger playing area, and a more continuous flow. But I think there’s still a lot of potential. A match can be broken down into specific “game states” based on ball location, player positioning, and team formations. Analysts can then identify which actions in certain states are most likely to lead to positive outcomes, like scoring a goal. These best-expectation actions could then inform coaching and training.</p> <p>I’ve heard that some Premier League teams already employ analysts in this way, and I imagine it’s a pretty fascinating job.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal-updates"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve mentioned this on the blog before, but one of the best things about moving to NYC for me has been being able to play soccer again. There was a tournament that had been running over the past few months, and it just wrapped up — our team came in second (after a grueling 3–2 loss in the finals). I ended up winning the golden boot with 14 goals and I actually learned a lot about both soccer and myself along the way.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the dynamics of incumbent politicians pt. 2</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2025/dynamics-of-politicians-pt2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the dynamics of incumbent politicians pt. 2"/><published>2025-05-25T10:49:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-25T10:49:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2025/dynamics-of-politicians-pt2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2025/dynamics-of-politicians-pt2/"><![CDATA[<p>This post is the long awaited (at least for myself) pt. 2 for the post <a href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/dynamics-of-politicians/"><em>the dynamics of incumbent politicians pt. 1</em></a>. It picks off on the model from last time by actually implementing it and creating a few visuals to look at to get a better sense of how we could look at the incentive structure of politicians from one strategy that economists would use to analyze the question.</p> <p>Now with that said the first thing I need to do tack on some addendum from part one of this post. The number of oversights one makes when the only thing editing is an AI gives me a bit of hope that it won’t steal <em>all</em> of our jobs. There’s not anything necessarily wrong per say with the model I discussed in part one but I really skimmed over some important details. First, the model I defined last in part one is a little bit different than the canonical job search question in that we have stochastic transitions and the politician’s choices affect this transition as well. Second, I definitely should have made the problems regarding the size of the policy space abundantly clear: I went for an ambitious model where the politician has a lot of choices of what they can do in each time, I’m trying to retain these choices but in doing so I have to sacrifice the extent to which the politician can consider each choice for the sake of having my code run in reasonable time.</p> <p>One other technique I forgot to mention (that I haven’t really seen in the econ literature/classes but is a pretty relevant method for reinforcement learning in ML) is Q-learning. This is a method that is very applicable in the scenario that I am discussing right now and I haven’t yet seen (although I am near positive that they exist) any problems in macro with stochastic transitions that depend on the action that the agent takes. In this case the politician’s transition probabilities into become elected in or “elected out” is itself dependent on both how much they spend on the elected and how they vote. For now, I did the value iteration by considering the expected value of the transition probability, but I’m also going to implement a Q-Learning thing as well just to see if they converge to the same value/policies (and for practice).</p> <div class="jupyter-notebook" style="position: relative; width: 100%; margin: 0 auto;"> <div class="jupyter-notebook-iframe-container"> <iframe src="/assets/jupyter/incumbent-politicians.ipynb.html" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; border-style: none;" width="100%" height="100%" onload="this.parentElement.style.paddingBottom = (this.contentWindow.document.documentElement.scrollHeight + 10) + 'px'"></iframe> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="econ-thoughts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This post is the long awaited (at least for myself) pt. 2 for the post the dynamics of incumbent politicians pt. 1. It picks off on the model from last time by actually implementing it and creating a few visuals to look at to get a better sense of how we could look at the incentive structure of politicians from one strategy that economists would use to analyze the question.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a very human struggle (in film)</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2025/human-struggle-in-film/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a very human struggle (in film)"/><published>2025-03-01T12:10:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-01T12:10:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2025/human-struggle-in-film</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2025/human-struggle-in-film/"><![CDATA[<p>The movies that I emotionally connect with the most are simple human stories of immense personal struggle with an emotionally meaningful ending. The ending itself need not necessarily be happy as long as it clearly resolves the main characters’ development throughout the movie. I’ve put a handful of my favorites below and want to talk a little bit about each of them.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Minari</strong>: One of my favorite parts of this movie is the soundtrack <em>Jacob and the Stone</em> — it’s a masterpiece that captures the essence of the movie quite well by combining elements of childlike wonder amidst a prevailing undertone of nostalgic sadness. For some reason, the movie itself reminds me a lot of all the nature parts of <em>Calvin and Hobbes</em> but involves a story of true American struggle.</li> <li><strong>The Pursuit of Happyness</strong> This is definitely my favorite Will Smith movie (followed closely by the <em>MIB</em> series). It’s a true story of a guy, Chris Gardner, who is going through tough financial times while trying to land a new job at a trading firm and taking care of his son by himself. The quintessential scene is at the end when Chris finally gets the job, and the audience understands how much it means to him given all the struggles he has endured to make it that far. It also seems like Will Smith’s performance was greatly aided by the fact that his son in the movie is also actually his son (Jaden) in real life.</li> <li><strong>Manchester by the Sea</strong>: This movie is what I call a masterclass in portraying “realistic grief.” Grief definitely manifests in very different ways for different people, but I personally think that the way Lee experiences his grief is very underrepresented in film — yet it reflects how a significant portion of people experience it. It doesn’t hit you when it “should” and does when it “shouldn’t.” It shows that healing doesn’t come in the form of momentous leaps at significant occasions like funerals but rather in small steps over time, like fishing trips with your nephew.</li> <li><strong>Beautiful Boy</strong>: The first time I watched this movie, I was emotionally moved for at least a week afterward. Even the thought of someone doing drugs made me inexplicably mopey and anxious because of what it did to the relationship between Timothée Chalamet’s character and his family. This movie and <em>The King</em> are what first made me start liking Timothée Chalamet, and I’m pretty eager to watch <em>A Complete Unknown</em> as well. Also, Steve Carell is a phenomenal dramatic actor (I admire comedic actors who can also excel in dramatic roles — like Robin Williams). One last thing I want to say about this movie is that it does a great job of showing the familial side of drug addiction.</li> <li><strong>The Perks of Being a Wallflower</strong>: It took me a while to get around to watching this movie (I only did a few months ago), but it’s definitely the one I can relate to the most. All the other movies on this list tell stories of people in vastly different physical or socioeconomic walks of life, but this movie is just the story of a high schooler in Pittsburgh. What I love most about this movie is that the foreshadowing was so subtle and that they didn’t show many of the trauma-inducing scenes on screen. Unbeknownst to me, this made the tension rise so gradually until it finally crescendoed with the music in the final breakdown scene, hitting like a truck. I still cry during that scene no matter how many times I’ve rewatched it. Plus, I love anything that has to do with Pittsburgh and feel an emotional connection to a lot of the places the friend group is also emotionally connected to — there are simply so many scenic places around the city that I’ve formed strong nostalgic bonds with.</li> <li><strong>Marriage Story</strong>: I knew this movie was all the rage when it first came out, and I actually tried to watch it but stopped 15 minutes in for some reason. It wasn’t until I revisited it during my senior year that I watched it the whole way through, and I didn’t regret it at all. Once again, the parts I enjoyed the most were the beginning and the ending — it tells a true human story that I’m sure many people have experienced. There’s no perfect happy ending, nor is it overly dramatized, but the movie keeps you engaged and emotionally connected the whole way through. Chef’s kiss.</li> <li><strong>Sound of Metal</strong>: The focus on sound in this movie was stellar, and the way it intertwined sound with Riz Ahmed’s character arc was masterful. I did not expect to like this movie as much as I did, but I connected deeply with the ending and thought it gave a new meaning to learning to accept one’s fate and making the best of it.</li> </ul> <p>The movies that I haven’t seen yet but feel are of a similar vein are <em>Eternal Sunshine of the Spotless Mind</em> and <em>If Beale Street Could Talk</em> (there is this piece called <em>Agape</em> from <em>If Beale Street Could Talk</em> that I love so much — I deeply wish the entire movie is thematically exactly like this song).</p> <p>Finally, in other news, the Oscars are happening this Sunday, and I’m looking forward to watching them. I haven’t watched as many of the movies up for nomination as I usually do, but I did watch <em>The Brutalist</em> — which, on a side note, I loved the opening shots/scene from. I think it conveys the true elation that immigrants from difficult parts of the world felt when they landed in the U.S. — the true immigrant experience from back in the day that you hear fading anecdotes about nowadays.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal-updates"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The movies that I emotionally connect with the most are simple human stories of immense personal struggle with an emotionally meaningful ending. The ending itself need not necessarily be happy as long as it clearly resolves the main characters’ development throughout the movie. I’ve put a handful of my favorites below and want to talk a little bit about each of them.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">economics communication in the public</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2025/econ-communication-in-public/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="economics communication in the public"/><published>2025-02-12T18:10:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-12T18:10:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2025/econ-communication-in-public</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2025/econ-communication-in-public/"><![CDATA[<p>In my mind, there is a big divide from the economics that I interact with on a daily basis and what the average american considers to be economics. As a high school student, I took the same view as the general public. I listened NPR in the mornings on the way to school where some “Senior Economist” from X company would qualitatively talk about the macroeconomics trends in some sector of the economy. During undergrad, however, a lot of my classes between math and cs were very quantitiatvely heavy and seemed to require deeper analysis than was found on the “Marketplace Morning Report”. It felt like there was a serious disconnect between the economics displayed in public and what I was experiencing myself in college. I had soon formed this idea that when people talk about macroeconomics in the news and in politics, it was using the tools of basic data analysis and the same coarse supply and demand graphs we studied in AP Macro and Micro; there was no sophisticated thought process underlying the intuition. This personal disastifaction with how imprecise I felt economics was handled even extented to the Federal Reserve and how Powell talked about why whatever rate decisions was being made. It felt like the important decisions were being made based on simple statements about how a price drop in thing A automatically implies that effect B occurs and I would cringe when I heard some econ commentary done by a non-economist that would not use the non-technical jargon that I had gotten used to. There did not seem to be many statements about the non-linear interactions economists think exist between all the different components of the economy or all the complex ways agents in our modeling process simultaneously solve their own optimization problems. I’ve since changed my view about how economics is communicated to an extent (which I will talk about shortly), but I still feel as if this divide is the quintessential issue in the relationship between public distrust and academia. I’ve been digging through the weeds that is the medical research on diet and personal health over the past year so I am well aware of the same divide in other academic fields, but I know both tranches of econ a lot more than other fields so I can speak to that better.</p> <p>Economics is obviously a hot button topic in politics because most everyone has to deal with money in some context and relies on it for their livelihood. People care about economic policy a lot but political ideologies about what is the right economic policy is very split. Among economists, however, my personal experience has been that people are not as much split along political lines as they are academic ideology wise when it comes to the actual economics that they are doing. To me, the academic ideology doesn’t seem to have as many direct links to the political divide as people consider it to have either. I feel like the perception of economists is that they look at graphs all day long and try to come up with some qualitative justifcation to explain why some lines go up and others don’t, which can be very suscpetible to one’s political views, when in reality there is a sophisticated machinery, that when explained step-by-step does seem to to be logically tractable to most people, behind the scenes. I’m not a complete optimist in that I know some groups are already completely entrenched in their beliefs, and at the end of the day, I don’t think that the divide will ever completely dissapear but I’m sure we can get in a better place than we are in right now. Relative to a field like medicin or quantum physics, there are many ways to contextualize the complexities in econ in an approchable manner and the topics are things that mostly do have a tangible impact that is easy to point out.</p> <p>On the other hand, I have now also come to develop a respect towards the way economics is communicated. I think it takes a special skill to be able to be aware of all the intricate dynamics at play and focus on the important factors or summarize this immensly complex network of relationships in a few sentences. Its something I defintely am not able to do well right now, but I am slowly getting there. I respect a lot of the economists here at the NY FED (and other big names who are good at communicating to outside of the academia bubble) since having started working here, but I still have my own additional ideas of how to better communicate ideas to help bridge the gap between polarized sides.</p> <p>I personally want to develop this communication skill as well. I’ve gotten a lot of feedback about how, for readers who are not in econ, the full econ themed blog posts really seem to lose them. Although I definitely won’t stop writing those types of posts (since those posts are the actual reason why I had an urge to write out my thoughts in blog format in the first place), I do want to put out more posts that try to bridge the gap between the economics that I interact with on a daily basis and something more easily understood by someone not in econ in a way where the rigour of the underlying analysis is communicated well. To know that when I say I think “The changes in thing A causes effect B”, it is understood that my reasoning is drawn out from a lot more than a few sentences of qualitative logic.</p> <p>As a final disclaimer, all this is not to say that econ doesn’t have its problems with inherently biased work. Yes, there are assumptions that have to be made to make the math/statistics work. Yes, there are many choices about why a model is built one way or the other. Yes, not every paper is constructed over the same dataset and the choice of which data to use in itself introduced bias. But in my personal experience, the rational for these decisions that must be made aren’t often related to political partisan lines. My main point is to say that I don’t think that economics is as strictly partisan in academia, and therefore people should not be as distrusting of opinions that do not align with themselves, as people consider it to be. It is very true that I am not the definitive voice of what goes on in all parts of academia, but I definitely do have a lot of restored faith in the Fed relative to my thoughts as an undergraduate student.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="econ-thoughts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In my mind, there is a big divide from the economics that I interact with on a daily basis and what the average american considers to be economics. As a high school student, I took the same view as the general public. I listened NPR in the mornings on the way to school where some “Senior Economist” from X company would qualitatively talk about the macroeconomics trends in some sector of the economy. During undergrad, however, a lot of my classes between math and cs were very quantitiatvely heavy and seemed to require deeper analysis than was found on the “Marketplace Morning Report”. It felt like there was a serious disconnect between the economics displayed in public and what I was experiencing myself in college. I had soon formed this idea that when people talk about macroeconomics in the news and in politics, it was using the tools of basic data analysis and the same coarse supply and demand graphs we studied in AP Macro and Micro; there was no sophisticated thought process underlying the intuition. This personal disastifaction with how imprecise I felt economics was handled even extented to the Federal Reserve and how Powell talked about why whatever rate decisions was being made. It felt like the important decisions were being made based on simple statements about how a price drop in thing A automatically implies that effect B occurs and I would cringe when I heard some econ commentary done by a non-economist that would not use the non-technical jargon that I had gotten used to. There did not seem to be many statements about the non-linear interactions economists think exist between all the different components of the economy or all the complex ways agents in our modeling process simultaneously solve their own optimization problems. I’ve since changed my view about how economics is communicated to an extent (which I will talk about shortly), but I still feel as if this divide is the quintessential issue in the relationship between public distrust and academia. I’ve been digging through the weeds that is the medical research on diet and personal health over the past year so I am well aware of the same divide in other academic fields, but I know both tranches of econ a lot more than other fields so I can speak to that better.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">food of nyc (oct-nov-dec)</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/food-OctNovDec24/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="food of nyc (oct-nov-dec)"/><published>2024-12-21T08:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-21T08:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/food-OctNovDec24</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/food-OctNovDec24/"><![CDATA[<p>There’s this app called Beli that a lot of New Yorkers have. It’s a food rating app where you can log all the restaurants and rank their relative placements (whether or not you liked place A over place B); the app then assigns a rating number based on the number rating of the relative choices you made. In general, I think it’s a pretty good way of getting people to stay consistent with ranking restaurants because I feel like it takes a lot more effort to think of a number than to decide qualitatively if one place was better than another and turns the process into a small mini-game. I am, however, notoriously bad at logging every place I go to into the app, which leads me to forget about some places that I genuinely want to keep track of (especially when people ask me for recommendations). The solution perhaps lies in just writing about them here, so here are a few notable places I’ve been to over the past couple months.</p> <ul> <li> <p><strong>l’artusi</strong>: For some reason, I had heard somewhere that this place was very overated and had that sense walking into the restaurant as well. I am (and Anouska for that matter), however, a sucker for both ricotta and buratta and our first app (which was a burrata crostone with fig and some other accoutrements) completely swayed me away from my preconceived notions about the place. There’s something about these middle to high upscale italian restaurants that deeply resonates with me; I feel like they really capture what I consider is the essence of italian cuisine, simple high-quality ingredients with very precise and intentional preparation. I’m not remembering every dish that we got from here but another famous dish of theirs that is a must have is their cacio e pepe. I eventually did rate this on my Beli and it’s pretty high up there.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Lucali</strong>: After months of thinking that I was going to go here, I finally made it and it is worth the hype by far. To be blatantly honest, I’ve seen pictures of the pizza before and didn’t think all too much about it, but both seeing it in person and tasting it is a completely different world. I’ve never had a New York style slice with this texture and it stands far above everybody else when it comes to this: the dough is unbelievably light while also maintaining incredible crisp. They are very particular with toppings and only offer a small list of eight-ish or so toppings. My favorite combo was surprisingly mushrooms and sweet pepper as opposed to the shallots and garlic. I still need to go another time to try the other items on their menu, the calzone and the rotating pasta that they change up but Lucali definitely makes it hard to choose my favorite pizza place between itself and L’Industrie Pizzeria (all these l’ places have something going on). At the end of the day it’s a battle between texture and flavor. All I can say definitely is that a pizza place with the texture of Lucali and the flavor creativity of L’Industrie would rule the world of New York Style slices. The next pizza place I have in my sights is Una Pizza Napoletana.</p> </li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/Lucali-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/Lucali-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/Lucali-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/Lucali.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The shallot garlic pizza </div> <ul> <li> <p><strong>Oxomoco</strong>: I’ve always felt like I’ve been to a michelin star restaurant in NYC, but other than a pastry popup from Eleven Madision Park, I cannot remember having been to another before Oxocomo. If that’s the case then Oxomoco is officially the first michelin star restaurant that I’ve been to (it has one star). It wasn’t mind blowing by any means but it was damn good food. We actually got two appetizers for free (due to some small hair in the tortilla chip), the guac n’ chips and the salsa n’ chips, both of which have given me some inspiration for when making my own guac and salsa. The main star of the show that I hard heard about were the tacos. I don’t think the brunch menu has all their tacos but I thoroughly enjoyed the ones I tried: the beet taco and the lamb barbacoa taco. I could speak a lot more about both in detail but the main idea takeaway is that Oxomoco does very well at finding a theme for each of their tacos and designing a well-rounded taste/presentation experience around them.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Hyderabadi Zaiqa</strong>: You wouldn’t expect it but Hyderbadi Zaiqa actually shows up on a decent number of “best in nyc” lists. I actually wasn’t the most hungry and in a eating state of mind when I came here so I don’t think our group ordered as optimally as we could have. I want to go again and make sure I’m treating this place the same as all the others, but out of what I did have, it was pretty decent.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Radio Bakery</strong>: It feels like ages since I’ve first visited Radio Bakery so I’m surprised that I haven’t talked about it yet. It may be the best bakery I have been to in NYC (with Dominique Ansel and Little Flower Cafe being a close contenders below) and it’s where I’ve had my favorite Pain au Chocolate (this is something that I try at each bakery that I go to if they have it). They don’t skimp on the chocolate at all on this croissant, it’s like a solid block of goodness surrounded by a perfect croissant, truly divine. They are also pretty popular for their foccacia sandwhiches which are also both very unique and quite well crafted. I’ve also bought a whole wheat sourdough loaf from them as well and made a couple sandwiches with it. I’m addicted to this place (even though I’ve only been twice).</p> </li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/Radio%20Bakery-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/Radio%20Bakery-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/Radio%20Bakery-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/Radio%20Bakery.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Foccacia Sandwiches </div> <ul> <li><strong>GupShup</strong>: I am recently been going on a crusade to find a upscale indian restaurant that blows my mind and GupShup was one of those on the list to try. It didn’t blow my mind (still trying to get a <em>Semma</em> res in the hopes that they manage to do it) but it was actually quite unique. First, I got a spicy sweet mango lassi, which is something that I’ve never had before but I now want to have all my mango lassis this way. They did some other interesting things like a tandoori cauliflower that I haven’t seen before that were pretty decent and they have this collab dessert with Caffe Panna (my favorite ice cream place) but still on the lookout for the mind-blowing indian restaurant.</li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/GupShup5-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/GupShup5-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/GupShup5-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/GupShup5.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/GupShup4-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/GupShup4-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/GupShup4-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/GupShup4.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/GupShup3-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/GupShup3-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/GupShup3-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/GupShup3.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/GupShup2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/GupShup2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/GupShup2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/GupShup2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/GupShup1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/GupShup1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/GupShup1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/GupShup1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> From left to right: pani puri, tandoori cauliflower, naan and some morels curry, chicket dum biryani, carrot halwa cake with caffe panna ice cream </div> <ul> <li><strong>Phoenicia Diner</strong>: The most sleeper place of them all. It’s currently at the top of my Beli list (which may just be a recency bias but I’ll re-evaluate later) but it is a decent ways out of New York. It’s something that you would go to during an Upstate New York roadtrip since it’s basically in the middle of nowhere. Anouska wasn’t nearly as mindblown as I was but I felt like they put so much care into everything on their menu, especially the breakfast items. Each breakfast item stood alone as the best version of that dish that I’ve ever had at a restaurant (I got some combination breakfast platter) and they partner heavily with local companies to source their ingredients. I am eagerly trying to find excuses to get back here.</li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/Phoenicia%20Diner-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/Phoenicia%20Diner-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/Phoenicia%20Diner-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Oct-Nov-Dec%20Food%20Post/Phoenicia%20Diner.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The Beet Reuben Sando </div> <p>Next week we’re getting back into econ stuff, specifically a part two to the politician’s incentive job search model.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="the-pittsburgh-palate"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There’s this app called Beli that a lot of New Yorkers have. It’s a food rating app where you can log all the restaurants and rank their relative placements (whether or not you liked place A over place B); the app then assigns a rating number based on the number rating of the relative choices you made. In general, I think it’s a pretty good way of getting people to stay consistent with ranking restaurants because I feel like it takes a lot more effort to think of a number than to decide qualitatively if one place was better than another and turns the process into a small mini-game. I am, however, notoriously bad at logging every place I go to into the app, which leads me to forget about some places that I genuinely want to keep track of (especially when people ask me for recommendations). The solution perhaps lies in just writing about them here, so here are a few notable places I’ve been to over the past couple months.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">finally back (post grad apps)</title><link href="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/finally-back/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="finally back (post grad apps)"/><published>2024-12-16T08:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-16T08:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/finally-back</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranay-gundam.github.io/blog/2024/finally-back/"><![CDATA[<p>It has been a while since my last post, mostly due to PhD applications and a big project going on at work, both of which have now pretty much ended which means we are getting back to the regularly scheduled weekly posts and boy do I have a lot in my drafts. This week, I just wanted to talk about random tid-bits here and there from the past two-ish months.</p> <p>Something that is most recent in my mind is a conversation I had with some friends who are not american citizens. One of them has already gotten picked in the H1B visa lottery but the other is still trying and we were observing how it felt like there was some innate country of origin bias in the process; either each country has their own lottery system or somehow immigrants from certain countries have better chances than others. Probability can be pretty deceiving, however, because based on how you define “feeling that an immigrant from one country has better chances than an immigrant from another country”, this statement and each immigrant having completely equal and independent chances can both be true. The example I had thought about was take a case where I know two australians and ten singaporeans all applying for an H1B visa and realistically each one has a 5% chance of getting chosen. It’s far more likely that at least 50% of my australian friends (aka one person) gets chosen than at least 50% of my singaporean friends getting chosen (aka five people) since you only need at least one australian to get selected but five singaporeans. If this percent of total population is the way you think about the probability of an australian getting an H1B vs a singaporean getting and H1B then even though the actual chance is the same because this country based definition depends on the immigrant population sizes from each country. You can also get pretty specific with the actual probabilities but I don’t feel like latexing the work for that all out right now other than saying if there are two countries with immigrant populations \(x, y\) where \(x&lt; y\) trying to get an H1B visa and the probability of any one person getting the visa in the lottery is \(p &lt; 0.5\). The chance of country X and country Y getting \(50\%\) of their population winning the lottery is \(\binom{x}{0.5x}p^{0.5x}(1-p)^{(1-0.5)x}\) and \(\binom{y}{0.5y}p^{0.5y}(1-p)^{(1-0.5)y}\) respectively (for the uninitiated, the \(\binom{x}{y}\) just means all the ways you can make groups of size \(y\) out of a total number of \(x\) many things). I’m being a little imprecise here for the sake of interpretability but two big caveats: this is all of course assuming that these country’s population sizes don’t have that much of an effect on the individual probability of winning the lottery, and I’m also assuming that both \(0.5x\) and \(0.5y\) are whole numbers. Long story short, the objective probability versus the way humans look at the world are quite different.</p> <p>In other news, I’m finally restarting a few projects that have been on hiatus for a while. Two of them are some video game ideas that I’ve had. The first, will take a bit of time and is a small dungeon crawl, but the second is a recreation of a small mobile game called “Landing Confirmed”. The concept behind this game is very simple, you have to navigate a rocket around a series of obstacles but the main draw is that the rocket is very fragile so colliding with any obstacle results in having to restart the level. The means by which you control the movement of the rocket, however, is the main draw for me. It’s a bit difficult to get used to but once you get a hang of it, the movement is so intuitive and leaves so much room for skill expression that gives the game a lot of potential. These game concepts and the feeling of mastering the mechanics are hard to explain to non-gamers but all you need to know is that the game is really satisfying to play and master. You essentially control the rocket by clicking on either the left or right side of the screen to control the left and right boosters respectively. The boosters contribute to both rotational and positional acceleration the same way an actual rocket would work. There is no nonsense letting you move horizontally on command, you have to first angle the rocket properly and then push with both boosters (except there is some more nuance in that obviously if you angle a rocket completely horizontally, or generally the more horizontal the axis of movement, the more speed you need to keep the rocket up right to avoid falling, but if you are trying to navigate through a set of obstacles then you need to manage your angles of travel and speed very accurately to avoid crashing).</p> <p>I’m not sure how far I’ll take my version of the game. I was thinking about some online multiplayer type shebang but we’ll see how I feel as I make progress. I do know that at the very least I want to create a basic version with one level and a rocket and match the feeling of the physics in the game. Regardless, you can find the current stage it is in <a href="https://github.com/pranay-gundam/landing-confirmed-engine">here</a>.</p> <p>There was a lot more that I wanted to talk about but not gonna lie I am completely blanking on everything. So in the spirit of not procrastinating I’m just going to shoot this one off. Next week is a food post (which I have been told are some of my more popular ones)!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal-updates"/><category term="miscellaneous-math-fun"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It has been a while since my last post, mostly due to PhD applications and a big project going on at work, both of which have now pretty much ended which means we are getting back to the regularly scheduled weekly posts and boy do I have a lot in my drafts. This week, I just wanted to talk about random tid-bits here and there from the past two-ish months.]]></summary></entry></feed>